<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>Alpine Style - Alpine, rock, ice and mixed climbing, ski touring, and photograhy by Jon Walsh</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</link>
 <description>Alpine, rock, ice and mixed climbing, ski touring, and photograhy by Jon Walsh</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Snowpatch East face photo with route lines of the free climbs</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2016/09/02/snowpatch_east_face_photo_with_route_lines_of_the_free_climbs</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Snowpatchwithlines.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My thursday night art project.  The east face of Snowpatch Spire with all the free routes on it.  I&#039;ve been meaning to create something like this for awhile.  I think the lines are pretty accurate for the most part.  Some of the main climbing features don&#039;t stand out perfectly from this angle, but it&#039;s a good angle of the entire face.  I&#039;m sure some of the gaps will fill in over the next few years!  &lt;i&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The summit ridge is 4th class, so the routes from Labyrinth and left have an average of about 100m of scrambling to the north summit.    &lt;/i&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/bugaboos">Bugaboos</category>
 <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 04:45:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">120 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Two new routes in a weekend! </title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2016/08/24/two_new_routes_in_a_weekend</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
A lot can be done in with some motivation and a good partner.  Colin Moorhead and I rolled out of golden at 6pm on friday August 19th, bound for the Bugaboos.  51 hours later, we were back having completed two new multi-pitch routes routes!   The stories and beta for “Minotaur Direct” and “Sick and Twisted” are below.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Minotaur Direct&lt;/i&gt; was a multi year project whose first ascent story goes something like this:  In 2011 Moorhead and I started on &lt;i&gt;Labyrinth&lt;/i&gt; and but ventured into new terrain aka Minotaur, on what’s now it’s 6th pitch.  We rejoined Labyrinth for it’s last three pitches but did 7 new ones, of which a couple included free variations of the aid route &lt;i&gt;Les Bruixes Es Pentinen.&lt;/i&gt;  Although it was a great day out and a memorable adventure, the King line with a direct start and finish awaited to be done.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In 2014, Michelle Kadatz and I started the direct route, cleaning many loose hanging blocks left precariously in place from the great flake that fell off the mountain in the late nineties.  We soon had a five pitch direct start established to the ledge system that Colin and I had traversed from &lt;i&gt;Labyrinth&lt;/i&gt; on.   Over several sessions from the July 2015 to July 2016, we continued to work on &lt;i&gt;Minotaur&lt;/i&gt; ground-up, cleaning the cracks, bolting the stations, and pushing the direct finish until only 60m below the summit ridge.  In 2015 when Michelle’s schedule was too busy, Alik Berg joined me up the first 5 pitches until we could branch out left and establish &lt;i&gt;Welcome to the Machine&lt;/i&gt; over two days. When Michelle’s schedule was busy in 2016, she told me to find another partner to finish the route with.  On a whim, I reached out to Colin, fully expecting his busy guiding schedule to get in the way.  Luckily he was psyched and cleared his schedule and made the 9 hour drive from Squamish.  We stumbled into Applebee camp by moonlight on the night of the 19th.  By 7 am, the next morning, we were crossing the moat on the edge of Cresent Glacier and climbing into the sunshine.  It took us about 14 hours up and down, which included us bolting a the last two belays and brushing the final 60 meters on rappel.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Our day went well as we settled into a nice rhythm, swapping leads up the 500-meter face.  It was fun watching Colin react to the route’s challenges and quality as he climbed it on-sight.  Top quality climbing every pitch with lots of variety is perhaps the best way to describe the route, with an emphasis on hand jams in upper pitches.  We expect this route will become a classic, as &lt;i&gt;Welcome to the Machine seems&lt;/i&gt; to be already.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The next day, despite feeling quite sore and completely full with satisfaction, we decided we might as well attempt climbing a shorter route before hiking out.  It so happened that Chris Brazeau and I had an un-sent project on Eastpost Spire, just ten minutes walk from camp.  Chris, who was at Applebee at the time,  even suggested we go for it without him, as it made sense to get it done before the short Bugaboo season ended.  Chris and I had done two-and-a-half laps on it in September 2015 and June 2016, putting the route up ground-up, on gear which was definitey sparse or minimal at times, and then adding a few bolts to it after.  Despite having both followed the second / crux pitch clean, we had both fallen off it on lead.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
So after multiple coffees and meals and camp, we headed up to give it a go, with no expectations given the fatigued state we were in.  This timehowever, as I felt my fingers wanting to slip off the crux holds, I found it in me to double the power and move through it, finally redpointing the pitch properly, as well as the rest of the route.  After Colin arrived at the belay at the end of the fourth pitch he said to me “This is sick and twisted”.  I agreed, and so the route name was born…  I think this route was a good find and it was somewhat surprising to discover something like this right beside the main climbers campground.  For me, it sure provided a fun few days of  climbing.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/snowpatch4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Minotaur is in red; Welcome to the Machine is in yellow; green dots are bolted belays, purple dots are gear belays.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Minotaur Direct&lt;/b&gt;, 5.11+ 16 pitches, East face of Snowpatch Spire&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
beta: bring two 60 ropes; a double rack of cams to #3 camelot, one #4; and triples of .3, .4, and .75.  One set of stoppers from #3 to #11.  12-14 draws half of which should be extendable.   All belays are bolted.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p1 - 30 meters 5.10-: step across the moat which gets harder as the season goes on.  Climb double cracks / opposing  flakes for about 10 meters until you’re able trend right, and easily up the big scoop.  Make a gear anchor before it steepens where you can find some good foot ledges.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p2 - 30 meters 5.10+: continue up the scoop via a thin corner crack, to a belay station at a good stance.  (Earlier in the season it’s possible to link pitches 1 and 2 with a 60m rope, but later in the season a 70m rope is needed for the link).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p3 - 30 meters 5.10+:  climb the corner above and pull through a small overhang to a stance. Step left and up a shallow left facing corner, until an easy ramp leads back right.  Follow this, hand traversing flakes until a belay station below a long left facing corner.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p4 - 45 meters 5.11+:  This pitch has 3 cruxes separated by good rests.  A thin tips corner gains a section of cool stemming.  When you get to a bolt clip it and face climb left to a stance on the arete.  Do not move up to the bolted station up and right, or you’ll have to down-climb 3 meters to continue sending! From the stance on the arete, move up and right back into the left facing corner, and follow it up past one more crux to the bolted station on a good ledge.  (Rappel note: the station skipped on this pitch is good to use while rappelling, but requires a directional piece to swing into it.  From here, rappel directly to the top of the big scoop in 55m)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p5 - 50 meters 5.10: After a couple body lengths of fist crack, pull a small overhang to a stance.  Rather than continue up the obvious corner, look up and you’ll see a bolt that can be reached via face holds.  Climb up to it, and move left into the next corner system left, which is much better due to the hand crack.  It leads to a fourth class ledge, which needs to be traversed up and left.  A belay station with ring hangers below a groove is for Minotaur, or, continue past it for five more meters to a belay station bellow a nice looking flake which is Welcome to the Machine.  If you miss the first protection bolt, the mountaineers version of this pitch exists and will get you to the same place but less directly, with sandy sections, loose rocks, rope drag, etc.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p6- 30 meters 5.10+:  Follow the groove up and right past two knifeblades to belay on a good ledge.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P7- 35 meters 5.11+:  Follow the obvious finger crack in left leaning corner, through the roof to a belay station.  This pitch could probably be called 5.10+ with one point of aid for those that find free-climbing the roof too difficult.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p8- 30 meters 5.11a:  Clip a bolt and traverse right on the slab to a shallow left facing, right leaning corner with a thin crack that takes excellent micro cams.  At it’s top, step left past two knifeblades into the main corner which is followed until a belay station is reached.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P9- 5.10 55m: This pitch is mostly 5.7ish with one little 5.10 bit.  Follow the corner up and slightly left.  After a short 5.10 sequence it will soon be possible to start trending back right to a belay a big ledge, a belay station, and an excellent bivi spot should one be needed.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p10- 25m 5.9:  Climb the best looking crack above the belay station towards a steeper wall above split by several cracks.  There is a belay station on the left.  (The original Minotaur route goes hard right from here)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p11 - 30m 5.11a:  Hand jams up the right hand crack give way to a thin finish in alcove, and a belay station.  (P10 and P11 can be linked)   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p12 35m 5.10+: climb the left crack out of the belay.  After about 5 meters, transfer back into the right one, which parallels the arete, and follow it to a belay at a nice perch.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p13 25m 5.9:  An easy chimney leads up and right to another nice belay perch on top of a pinnacle.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p14 30m 5.11c:  A left leaning crack.  Bouldery moves past three bolts soon give way to easier crack climbing that leads to a big ledge and a station. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p15 28m 5.11c: a short corner with a fist crack leads to a ledge.  A beautiful thin hand splitter continues up the headwall above to a belay station on a ledge.  This pitch is why you need the third .75 camelot on the rack.    &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p16 35m 5.10+:  Keep going up the same crack which has now kicked back slightly in angle and become more positive.  A 60m rappel gets you back down to the last two pitches.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The North summit is about 150 meters of 4th class scrambling away.  Stay on east side of the ridge if you go for it.  &lt;br /&gt;
Rappel the route&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
All grades for both routes are suggested.  Any feedback on grades is welcome!   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Sick and Twisted&lt;/b&gt;, 5.12a, 5 pitches, Eastpost Spire 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Eastpost3.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A good option for a short day, bad weather, or just something to play around on.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rack: double rack of camelots from #.3 to #2, one #3, one of each size below .3;  6-8 stoppers.  If rappelling, a 70m rope is needed although two ropes is nicer, especially if you want to haul a pack.  All belays are bolted.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P1 25m 5.11d: Climb up and trend right to a corner.  follow it out below a roof until it’s possible to pull the roof, then up the groove to a belay.  This pitch has four protection bolts.  The in the first half of this pitch is unfortunately a bit crumbly but the rest of the route is a lot better.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P2 30m 5.12a:  Climb up a few meters, then traverse below the big roof to the left for about 15m until it’s possible to climb up a left facing corner to a belay on a good ledge.  The 12a grade is a combination of the sustained 11+ climbing and the intimidation of the traversing style.      (35m to the ground from here)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p3 30m 5.11a:  Start up a left facing corner to a ledge, move left to the next left facing corner and climb it past some funky features.  Move right to another big ledge but make steep moves upwards at it’s left edge, and belay at a good stance at the right end of the big hanging slab.  There may be a bit of suspect rock on this pitch, but much better than the first one.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P4 25m 5.10d:  Cross then hanging slab past four bolts, then up and across to belay below some short steep crack lines.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P5 20m 10d:  start up the corner then head up the middle of three cracks.  (the left one is The Flaming Hack Arete)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
You can either walk off (down the trail on the other side of the ridge), or rappel.  From the top, a 55m rappel makes it to a bolt station on the slab below, rightness the edge and about 10 meters away from Sheldons Corner.  Another 50m rappel hits the ground. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A few action shots of the two route: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/snowpatch%201.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle Kadatz on P11 of Minotaur direct, 5.11a
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minotaur%205.jpg&quot; /&gt;Colin on pitch 15, of Minotaur Direct  5.11c thin hands!  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/sickandtwisted.jpg&quot; /&gt;Chris Brazeau on the first pitch of Sick and Twisted.  There are now a couple more bolts in this section.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00989.jpg&quot; /&gt;Me on P4 of Sick and Twisted, the hanging slab pitch.  Photo:  Chris Brazeau
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/sickandtwisted2.jpg&quot; /&gt;Chris on the last pitch of Sick and Twisted.  A fun finish!   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/bugaboos">Bugaboos</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 03:52:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">119 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Cupcake Conspiracy</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2016/06/21/the_cupcake_conspiracy</link>
 <description>&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cupcake.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Cupcake Conspiracy
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After failing to find any alpine routes in decent shape late last October, due to extremely mild conditions, plan B landed us in the Ghost River area with our sights set on establishing a rock route up some untouched blue streaks on a virtually untouched wall in Bonanza Bay.  Michelle roped gunned Bonanza and I followed with a pack full of ropes, bolts and a drill.  We came in from above figuring out most of the intended line on the way down, and got it mostly bolted in the next day and half before the season’s first snow storm brought progress to a chilly halt.  It was a different yet enjoyable adventured discovering a way up a wall of high quality limestone with virtually no options for any natural gear.  Six months later, we finally made it back, drilling the crux pitch on lead, and sending it along with the rest of the route in a fun day.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Lots more potential around here for more routes like this one, and having two or three like on the wall would allow for bigger days. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Beta:&lt;br /&gt;
5 pitches, 150m, 5.11+   First ascent Michelle Kadatz and Jon Walsh, June 12, 2016.   A fun bolted route in the on mostly excellent rock in the middle of the South facing Bonanza Bay wall, about halfway between Bonanza and the Bonanza decent gully.  All belay stations are equipped with Fixe rap rings.  16 draws needed and 2 or 3 of them should be extendable.  Two ropes is best for getting back down.  A 70-meter rope works for almost all rappels although at this point, it’s unknown if it will get you down pitch 2 but likely very close.       &lt;br /&gt;
Lots more potential around here for more routes like this one, and having two or three like on the wall would allow for bigger days. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The grades aren’t confirmed although some friends repeated it the day after we finished it.  Perhaps some more feedback will help confirm the grades. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 1,  5.10a 10 bolts, 35-meters.  It starts behind two good sized spruce trees about 50 meters right of Bonanza, and should be easy to find.   Follow the bolt line to good ledge.     &lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 2, 5.11c/d  15 bolts, 40-meters.   Face climb up and right from the belay towards a blue-streaked corner.  Head left at a roof (extendable draws useful here), and continue trending up and left around the corner to small ledge and a station.  &lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 3, 5.11d/12a 7 bolts,  15-meters.  Head up and right towards a roof, before making a crux move back left through it, which leads to a station at a decent stance.    &lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 4, 5.10b 10 bolts, 35-meters.  Prickly featured holds lead up perfect grey rock to an anchor at a big ledge on the right.  &lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 5, 5.10d 11 bolts, 35-meters.  Straightforward face climbing to the rim.    
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/rock_climbing">Rock climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/the_ghost_river">The Ghost River</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2016 03:23:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">118 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Scotland Trip Report 2016</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2016/02/08/scotland_trip_report_2016</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Since participating in the BMC winter meet two years ago, I’ve been dreaming of returning to the Scotland.  Although it has some of the most persistently appalling weather imaginable, it’s stunningly beautiful, and is home to one of the most interesting styles of winter climbing I know of.  A strict code of ethics prevents any bolting in the mountains.  The rock is typically granitic and well featured, and the wild north atlantic weather plasters the cliffs in ice, rime, snow and verglas, thus creating conditions where you’ll often be dealing with 4 or 5 different mediums at time.  Mix that with some frozen turf and neve, it’s about as mixed as it gets.   Although all the climbing I did seemed quite sustained and technically in the M6 to M8 range, placing the protection was often the crux as most of it needed to be pounded in.  Camming devices were almost completely useless!  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
During the last week of January and first week of February 2016, a small group of Canadians including myself, Michelle Kadatz, Paul McSorley, Marc Andre Leclerc, Ian Welsted, and Paul Bride, settled into a little rental cottage in the village of Glen Coe, a little village situated in Scottish highlands. Over 12 days, the milder than average weather we experienced only permitted about 6 days of climbing, which I suppose isn’t too bad for a trip of this nature.  A couple of days were spent taking the gear for a walk, also known as hill walking, only to find the cliffs “black” and out of condition due to rainy weather with higher than mountain top feeling levels.  It needs to be frozen / look white in order to preserve the turf, but fortunately, as soon as the temps drop, many routes are instantly good to go.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Down time involved a good mixture of cruising around the country side sampling the local flavours, checking out castles, lochs, pubs, towns, and couple of trips to the worlds biggest indoor climbing gym in Ratho to keep the form.   All said and done it was a great trip, the locals were really helpful and I look forward to honing my mixed climbing skills in highlands many more times.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Much of climbing we did was on Ben Nevis, and I also visited Stob Coire Nan Lochan at Glen Coe, and Coire An Lochan in the Cairngorms.  My favourite route of trip, and also the hardest one I climbed was definitely Knuckelduster on Ben Nevis.  It was so plastered in rime and verglas that route finding was really difficult as there are many small precarious holds and very in obvious gear through the crux, although I&#039;ve never climbed anything with such a truly mixed feel to it.  It was definitely a battle to put it together and was of very high intensity at much of the time.  A really cool line that I’m stoked to have on-sighted, especially considering difficult conditions.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scottish grades don&#039;t make a lot of sense to me, but I&#039;ve never really felt that grades mean very much in this style of climbing.    
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The following photos are some highlights and maore interesting photos of what we got up to: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00567.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michelle climbing the Gargoyle cracks during a link-up of Hobgoblin (VII,7) into Babylon (VII,8) - Number 3 gully buttress of Ben Nevis - a fun warm up day
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00579.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michelle and Marc enjoying some blustery conditions on the rim after Michelle and I finished Hobgoblein / Baylon, and Marc had just finished his 8th route of the day!  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0228.jpg&quot; /&gt; The coveted Stob Coire Nan Lochan.  A nice venue to have in our backyard, stacked with classic routes up to 200 meters high
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_1394.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Me starting up the first pitch of what I called Impulsive 
Inclination (VIII,8).  It starts at the base of the Unicorn (summer start to this route?), and heads 
up and left.  After 20 meters, it joins Inclination for its second pitch
which I linked all the way to a big terrace after 40 meters of 
climbing.   It may or may not be a couple of new variations to the 
routes around it, but either way it was top quality climbing and a lot 
of fun!  &lt;i&gt;photo: Michelle Kadatz&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0264.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Looking right from the end of the of the first pitch, Ian Welsted seen here, and Paul McSorley were trying to find the way on Scanzor (IX,9) - Stob Coire Nan Lochan
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0249.jpg&quot; /&gt; Looking up p2 of Impulsive Inclination.  It climbs an 
unprotectable series of edges up and left for about 7 meters towards the
obvious hand crack, up that for a bit, and then moved right into a groove.  After about 20
meters, it joined Tilt which was followed to the top.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetFileAttachment.jpg&quot; height=&quot;683&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; /&gt;Here is Paul Bride&#039;s view of me, leading the second pitch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Upon reaching the summit, we met up with Marc Andre who had just soloed 5 routes!  Here&#039;s a link to a raw video clip of what he had to say about his day: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R0nr9pa5To4&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R0nr9pa5To4 &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00655.jpg&quot; /&gt; The next route we did and the highlight of the trip for me was Knuckleduster, a burly VIII,9 on Ben Nevis.  Here&#039;s Michelle following the first, and a link to Greg Boswell&#039;s take on the route &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scottishwinter.com/?p=2264&quot;&gt;http://www.scottishwinter.com/?p=2264&lt;/a&gt; with a cool photo of him entering the crux, although for me is was completely plastered white with rime and looked a bit different.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/12633464_10156520270625084_8777380927217893482_o.jpg&quot; /&gt;Rocio Siemens snapped this shot of me (center of photo) making the final traverse left to the belay stance at the end of the crux second pitch.  It was the third traversing bit of this wild pitch that involved a nice mix of corner, face and arete climbing, and is a cool overview of one of Scotland&#039;s finest crags.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00663.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Michelle making precarious moves around the arete to the belay back in main corner of the summer route, at the end of pitch 2 on Knuckleduster.  It&#039;s about the same spot I&#039;m in in the previous photo.  This was definitely the hardest pitch of the trip as it plastered white with  rime, and coated in verglas, which made for very tricky route finding and gear placements.  It also felt a little on the bold side as I was never quite sure whether or not I could trust my gear, although judging by how hard it was to clean for Michelle, it must&#039;ve of been adequate!   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00678.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle happy to be off the traverse and at the anchor.  A week later and she still seems traumatized by this pitch!  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_1415.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Me climbing pitch 3 of Knuckleduster with burning forearms.  I think this is the direct finish or the summer route.  A nice crack in the right wall of the corner provides sustained climbing up a slightly overhanging for about 15 meters, followed by a short ledge traverse and another 15+ meters of slightly easier terrain to the top.  As usual, the crux was hammering nuts into the iced up crack.  &lt;i&gt;Photo: Michelle Kadatz  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00691.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Marc Andre Leclerc trying to find the Coire an Lochan in the Cairgorms, in sustained 60 mph winds (at least that what was forecasted and i don&#039;t doubt they were at least that!) and zero visibility.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00713.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Marc Andre Leclerc on sighting the first pitch of Happy Tyroleans (X, 10) in howling winds and constant snow.  Fortunately the overhanging nature of the pitch kept too much snow piling up on the ledges.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00719.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Marc Andre Leclerc following the second pitch of Happy Tyrolean.  Vertical climbing soon kicked back a bit, and storm snow was piling up fast!   Also a great pitch, and about two grades easier than the first one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/DSC00751.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Scotland is famous for its pubs and this was our local watering hole.  From L to R: Marc Andre Leclerc,  Ian Welsted, Will Woodhead, Paul McSorley, Paul Bride, Jon Walsh.  Photo: Michelle Kadatz&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/scotland">Scotland</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 14:28:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">117 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The East face of Snowpatch, the gift that keeps on giving</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2015/08/05/the_east_face_of_snowpatch_the_gift_that_keeps_on_giving</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Over the last decade or so, the 500-meter high East face of Snowpatch Spire has been transforming into one of the finest alpine rock faces in North America.  What used to be a face known primarily as an aid climbing venue, is now covered in free-climbing lines, although mostly difficult ones, usually reqiuring at least a couple pitches of 5.12.  But perhaps the most amazing thing about it is that almost every pitch is good!  I don&#039;t think there&#039;s another mountain in western Canada that can boast that!  Like a big crag offering pure rock climbing in the alpine, it offers an easy approach from the nearby campground, belays on most routes are mostly bolted, there are no &amp;quot;approach&amp;quot; pitches, and there&#039;s no tedious summit ridge.   The climbing is almost entirely traditionally protected, although most routes have a few protection bolts where cracks need to be conected by face moves, and face holds are plentiful.    It has been one of my favorite zones for over ten years now. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Last season, Michelle Kadatz and I investigated the sector in the Bugaboo guidebook where the great flake fell off the lower middle section of Snowpatch Spire, taking the first three pitches of several routes including &lt;i&gt;Les Bruines Es Pentinen, Deus Ex Machina, and the original Sunshine Wall &lt;/i&gt;with it.  The obvious scoop at the bottom went ok, but the next 80 meters required extreme care to remove the left over debris from the major rockfall.  Once it was gone, it didn&#039;t take much to buff it into a nice free climb and a fairly moderate one by East face of Bugaboo standards.  After five pitches, we had established &lt;i&gt;Minotaur Direct, &lt;/i&gt;which seemed like a better start than the original version that climbed the lower pitches of &lt;i&gt;Labyrinth &lt;/i&gt;and traversed over.  We returned this year, adding stations and continuing up the amazing middle section of Minotaur, a route I put up several years ago with Colin Moorhead.  We gave this a good clean up too as this section of the wall is becoming a popular option amongst both Bugaboo regulars and visiting climbers.  People seem psyched to have good pitches within a close proxitimity to Applebee and often set out to climb only half the face.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alik Berg and I teamed up in mid July to venture out left from Minotaur into the obvious corner system that splits the big roof in the middle of the face where the &lt;i&gt;Deus Ex Machina&lt;/i&gt; goes.  We were blown away by the quality of the climbing and the softest pitch gradewise out of all the routes to go through this continuous roof system that runs the width of the face.  Above it we ventured into new terrain but a couple of mossy cracks slowed progress about ten pitches up.  We cleaned them out and rappeled.  Two weeks later we were back with plans to finish the line.  On the first day we climbed the first four pitches and fixed our two ropes.  This allowed a bit of head start for a bigger day the next day.  It was nice to sleep in the evening after hiking up, and fun to have Taran Ortlieb join us for this.  The next day, we ascended the two lines, then made the continuous free ascent to the summit, adding four more pitches above our previous high point and sending every pitch first try!  A very satisfying day, on a fun route with a lot of varied climmbing.           
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_2257%20copy.jpg&quot; height=&quot;1350&quot; width=&quot;900&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The East face of Snowpatch Spire with the line of ascent.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9311.jpg&quot; /&gt;Taran Ortlieb joined us as we fixed two ropes on the first four pitches.  Here he is crossing the moat between edge of the glacier and the face.  Exactly four weeks earlier, it was easy to step across the gap and be standing on the ledge his left hand is at.  As the summer goes on, and the snow melts back from the rock, the first pitch can get 5-10 meters longer and a grade or two harder!  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9323.jpg&quot; /&gt;Taran a few meters higher on the first pitch, now enjowing perfect hand jams on perfect granite.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9331.jpg&quot; /&gt;Alik leading off on the second pitch of 5.10 tips.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9359.jpg&quot; /&gt;Having Taran join us to climb the first four pitches and fix our ropes, allowed me to lead the fourth pitch, and then take photos of Alik leading it.  It&#039;s got four 5.11 sections to it over 45 meters and is delightful to climb!      
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9374.jpg&quot; /&gt; Another from the fourth pitch - Some face moves protected by a bolt connect two corner systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9393.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alik hiking last crux of the fourth pitch with a combination of chimneying, steming, and edge pulling.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9411.jpg&quot; /&gt; Alik climbing the splitter flake at the start of the 6th pitch. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9436.jpg&quot; /&gt; JW in the first of four cruxy sections on the 7th pitch - the roof pitch of &lt;i&gt;Deus Ex Machina&lt;/i&gt;, previously A3.  It&#039;s the only one that we think shared any terrain with any of the old aid routes. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9440.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Alik nearing the top of the 55-meter 9th pitch.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9447.jpg&quot; /&gt;Alik starting up the 10th pitch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9460.jpg&quot; /&gt;Some fine heel work high on Snowpach, with magical jugs in the all the right places; Alik getting starting on pitch 12.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9462.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
Alik on pitch 12 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9464.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
Another from pitch 12 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_9468.jpg&quot; /&gt;On the North Summit of Snowpatch with the summit ornament, and views of the Howsers. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;Welcome to the Machine&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
5.11+, 13 pitches&lt;br /&gt;
First ascent:  Pitches 1-5 - Michelle Kadatz and Jon Walsh;  Pitches 6-13: Alik Berg and Jon Walsh &lt;br /&gt;
August 2nd, 2015&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p1 - 30 meters 5.10-; step across the moat which gets harder as the season goes on.  Climb double cracks / flake for about 10 meters until you’re able trend right, and easily up the big scoop.  Make a gear anchor before it steepens where you can find some good foot ledges.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p2 - 30 meters 5.10+; continue up the scoop via a thin corner crack, to a belay bolted belay a good stance.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p3 - 30 meters 5.10+;  climb the corner above and pull through a small overhang to a stance. Step left and head up a shallow left facing corner, until an easy ramp leads back right.  Follow this, hand traversing flakes until a bolted station below a long left facing corner.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p4 - 45 meters 5.11+;  A thin tips corner gains a section of cool stemming.  When you get to a bolt clip it and face climb left to the arete.  Don’t move it up to the bolted station up and right or you’ll have to down-climb 3 meters to continue sending! from the stance on the arete, move up and right back into the left facing corner, and follow past one more tips crux to the bolted station on a good ledge.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p5 - 50 meters 5.10 ; After a couple body lengths of fist crack, pull a small overhang.  A #5 camelot is useful here for the crux move.  Rather than continue up the obvious corner, look up and you’ll see a bolt.  Climb up to it, and move left into the next corner system which is much better.  It leads to a fourth class ledge, which needs to traversed up and left.  A bolt below a groove is the start of Minotaur.  Continue past it for five more meters to a two bolt station bellow a nice looking flake.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p6 - 35 meters 5.10;  Climb the flake up, then hand traverse it left.  It turns into a walkable ledge.  At it’s end, move up and left though small overlaps, then face climb left, and then back right to a bolted station. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p7 - 45 meters 5.11+; This is the roof pitch of Deus Ex Machina.  Move left off the belay, and then climb up a small right facing corner on face holds.  Move left into the main left corner and follow it though a series of small roofs to a bolted anchor. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p8 - 60 meters 5.10;  Climb the right hand crack for five meters to a ledge, Move left into a corner which is wide but easy.  Follow this to a good ledge.  Continue up another short right facing corner with couple of tricky moves and make a gear belay another good ledge, with some very nice looking corners up to the left.  This pitch might be better to split into two as rope drag is a factor.  Either way, a gear station needs to be made.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p9 - 55 meters 5.11;  An amazing pitch! Start by climbing double cracks, with a mix of gear and bolts for protection (3 protection bolts total).  At a small stance there’s a fixed wire and a bolt for an optional belay, however the FA team linked the next 30 meters of sustained 5.10 to a great ledge and bolted belay.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p10 - 40m meters 5.11-;  climb the nice finger crack up and right.  After a section of fist crack, two bolts on your left traverse to a ledge system, and a two bolt anchor at the far left of it.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p11 - 50 meters 5.10-;  A clean corner above goes from hands to fists to off-width.  After it gets too wide for a # 5 camelot, two body lengths of easy lay-backing passes it and gets you to easier terrain with small gear options.  Continue up the groove above to a two bolt station below some black overhangs.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p.12 - 25 meters 5.11+;  The last two pitches were nearly linked on the first ascent with 68m rope, but this is not recommended.  Start by climbing through some overhangs with some great and unlikely moves.  Belay at a good ledge.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
p.13 - 45 meters 5.11 ; Follow the crack up and left, until a big ledge is reached.  This pitch is a bit dirty but will clean up with a more ascents.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A scramble for a couple of ropelengths up and left gets you to the North Summit.  You will pass the top station of Sendero Norte on the way which is probably the cleanest descent option.  Of course if you don&#039;t know it, it might be more difficult.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The other decent option is as follows: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
At the big ledge at the top of the last pitch, a sling around a pinch between boulders was used for the first rappel, to get back to the top of pitch 11.  From here, rappel to a nut station about 10 meters climbers right of the station at the top of pitch ten.  Careful of the rope eating crack below.  Best to just rappel to the top of pitch 9 from here to keep the rope out of the crack.  Then rappel to the obvious bivy ledge, on skiers left.  On the far side of this ledge, rappel down Minataur on bolted stations.  The first one is 55m.  The second one is 30 m and it’s best to clip a bolt on the way down as a directional.  Another 55m steep rappel gets you back to the big ledge at the top of pitch 5.  Continue down the pitches you’ve already climbed.  From the top of pitch 4, it&#039;s about a 65 meter rappel to the top of pitch 2, so if you have 60 meter ropes, it&#039;s best to place a directional or two to get into the optional station on pitch 4, and then rap to the top of pitch 2 from there.  One more 50-55 rappel puts you on the glacier.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Recommended rack:&lt;br /&gt;
2 x 60m ropes&lt;br /&gt;
Double set of cams from tips to #3 camelot. &lt;br /&gt;
Triple set from tight fingers to loose fingers (#.3, #.4, #.5 camelots)&lt;br /&gt;
1 #4 camelot, 1 #5 camelot&lt;br /&gt;
One set of nuts&lt;br /&gt;
12-15 quick draws (half of them should be extendable)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/bugaboos">Bugaboos</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 01:39:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">116 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Kahveology</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2015/01/26/kahveology</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
KAHVEOLOGY - (The science of coffee)&lt;br /&gt;
160m, M8 WI5  First ascent by Jon Simms and Jon Walsh, Jan 23rd, 2015
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0412.jpg&quot; width=&quot;710&quot; /&gt;Simms on the approach
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Jonny “the Simmulator” Simms and I had a good Man Yoga practice at the Storm Creek Headwall, in Kootenay National Park.  Despite much thinner that usual ice-conditions this year, the end result was Kahveology, a new 4-pitch mixed route, that’s essentially the direct start to final ice pillar of Check Your Head, another route I co-authored a couple years ago with Jason Kruk and Joshua Lavigne.   Kahveology means the Science of coffee, and it’s a also a company in Portland that named one of their coffee blends Man Yoga, after the route on the Stanley Headwall that Simms and I authored, and Joshua Lavigne made an entertaining video of.  We were so honoured they named the main blend served in their shop after us, we named our latest route after them, to complete the circle, as well as a thank you for sending some of their crucial beans our way!  Being the serious coffee fiend that I am, I would definitely drink it all the time if it was closer to home.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0415.jpg&quot; height=&quot;1280&quot; width=&quot;960&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Crucial coffee in necessary for Man Yoga
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyways, while descending from Check Your Head by headlamp, straight down, rather than reversing a couple traverses we had made, I couldn’t help but notice the immaculate, featured, overhanging limestone that directly lead to a tongue of ice that slithered halfway down it, flowing from the pillar.  What particularly caught my eye was the abundance of natural protection, somewhat rare for a steeper-than-vertical angle, and I immediately planned to come back someday to attempt it.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0433.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Through the crux of the first pitch 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
That finally came a week ago, as Michelle and I skied up there on a cold day.   I did get on it, but unfortunately, couldn’t make it go bolt free, like I’d been dreaming about.   The route starts with about ten meters of easy stuff to get to the back of a cave.  Unsurprisingly, the back of the cave was chossy, and I had to place two bolts just to get into the steep climbing.  Then two more bolts got placed as I blew my gear and tools out on body weight placements.  With four bolts placed through the steepest and hardest pulls, I got to a nice crack which marked the beginning of what’s probably the best stretch of limestone I’ve ever dry tooled on.  Eventually, I placed two more bolts, perhaps unnecessary ones (although I was pretty psyched to clip them on the redpoint burn a week later), before getting to a fixed-nut rappel anchor left from a couple years ago, which marked the end of the day.   Many thanks to Michelle for enduring a long cold belay.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0434.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Higher on the first pitch but still 15 meters to go
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Six days later, the stars aligned for us.   It was much milder making for perfect conditions, the track was still good, and Simms and I made it to the base in 2 hours at a casual pace.  With the route prepped, I was able to get the redpoint, and was even egged on to make it a “mega-pitch” and keep climbing all the way to a small ledge, just above the bottom of the ice.  Definitely one of the best pitches I’ve done in the Rockies.  After a few steep pulls out the cave, the angle eases to vertical to slightly overhanging for about 30-meters, with numerous bulges to negotiate.  Perfect torquing cracks and incut holds, made for really fun sustained climbing, with enough stances to shake out from, although never a hands free position until the belay.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FZsjr0QNkPI&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;A raw unfiltered video of on the second pitc&lt;/a&gt;h
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ERNeikx0ow&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;And on on the fourth &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The second pitch was also new and of similar quality, although it followed a fragile strip of ice that on average was an inch thick and a foot wide.  By the time we were done it, the snow was falling so we had to hurry as a 2000’ couloir was above the route.  Sure enough, it wasn’t long before huge sloughs started coming down at frequent intervals.  We split the last 60-meters of ice into two pitches as there was a good belay spot on the right below a rock overhang and we only had a 50-meter rope.  We had also brought the drill and installed bolted anchors the whole way right to the top, with hopes it will entice others to get out and try this incredibly high quality route.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0446.jpg&quot; /&gt;starting pitch 2
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0470.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Higher on pitch 2
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0475.jpg&quot; /&gt; Simms on pitch 3
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0481.jpg&quot; /&gt; me following it
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0491.jpg&quot; /&gt;pitch 4 as the storm intensifies
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0496.jpg&quot; /&gt;rappelling from the top.  We had a lot of snow come down on us and around us over the course of four rappels  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Beta:&lt;br /&gt;
Approach: Park at the Stanley Headwall.  Walk or ski for two to three hours depending on conditions.  It is one of the closest to the road on the Storm creek headwall, and you can see the upper ice from the highway.  I believe it’s probably climbable most years.  &lt;br /&gt;
-2 ropes, 50-meters will suffice if you have them and want to carry less weight.&lt;br /&gt;
-12-14 quick draws, which should include a few long ones&lt;br /&gt;
-6 screws, mostly 10-13 cms&lt;br /&gt;
-stoppers from 4-11&lt;br /&gt;
-Pitons: optional….I placed one #3 Pecker and left it fixed on the second pitch&lt;br /&gt;
-I had a double rack of cams up to #3 camelot, and 1 #4.  I didn’t need much in the really small sizes.  I did place two #3’s on the fist pitch, but would probably have been ok with a single set in the hand crack sizes.   Definitely double up in the .3, .4, and .5 camelot sizes, and maybe a bit more.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There is a sheltered spot below a small overhang about 20 meters down and lookers right of the route to gear up, and leave your skis and packs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0377.jpg&quot; /&gt;THe route as seen from the approach 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ERNeikx0ow&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ERNeikx0ow&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 1:  45m M8 - From the highest point of snow below the ice, trend slight right up easy, scrappy, mixed snow ice and rock.  A fist crack provides protection for a steep bodylength to the chossy back of the cave.  Follow 4 bolts up and left requiring a few honest pulls, to get to a nice crack.  Follow that up.  It soon passes two more bolts and a fixed nut from the old rappel anchor.  After those, trend right, then back left to a bulge below the ice which is used to gain a small ledge and a bolted anchor on the right.  Be sure to put a runner on the first bolt, a medium length draw on the second bolt, and extend other cams etc. where necessary to reduce rope drag. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 2: 50m M6 R - This might be much easier on fatter years.  An 80-degree ice goulotte, with occasional rock pro for 15-meters, leads to average 60-degree terrain.  It was a very consistent 3 cm thick the entire way for us, and was unprotectable for 30 meters after the angle kicked back.  A fall would be serious.  Fortunately, the ice we had was of excellent quality making it a reasonable endeavour.  The bolted anchor is about 5 meters right of the pillar.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 3: 30m WI5 - Steep ice, thin and hard to protect at the first, but it does improve.  A bolted anchor is on the right below a rock roof.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 4:  25m WI4 - Straight forward ice climbing.  The bolted anchor is about 3-4 meters above the top of the ice in some rock.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/ice_mixed_climbing_0">Ice / mixed climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/kootenay_national_park">Kootenay National Park</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/storm_creek_headwall">Storm Creek Headwall</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2015 04:47:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">115 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Plum</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2014/11/10/the_plum</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The Plum&lt;/b&gt;  WI6 M7, 120m, first ascent: &lt;a href=&quot;http://marcleclerc.blogspot.ca/&quot;&gt;Marc-Andre Leclerc&lt;/a&gt; and Jon Walsh Nov. 8, 2014&lt;br /&gt;
A new traditional mixed route with no bolts, at the Storm Creek Headwall, Kootenay National Park B.C.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7717.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Marc on the approach, with the route marked in red, the belays in green, and the snowslope approach in thick red.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On Saterday November 8th, Marc-Andre and I completed the first ascent of &lt;i&gt;The Plum&lt;/i&gt;, a line that’s been in the back in the mind, and in my dreams for the past decade.  It follows a slender flow of ice that drips down the nose of a steep butress, creating funky mushrooms, daggers and pillars, that are a real treat to climb on.    I had attempted it approximately ten years ago with my ice mentor Rich Marshall.  After climbing a pitch of steep ice out of the big cave which eventually became the first pitch of &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/21932853&quot;&gt;The Peach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, another fine addition to Rockies trad mixed by&lt;a href=&quot;http://raphaelslawinski.blogspot.ca/2011/03/peach.html&quot;&gt; Raphael Slawinski&lt;/a&gt;, Rich proceeded to lead what was the wildest pitch he had ever led - he later confessed, as well as one on the craziest leads I’d ever witnessed.  Committed after climbing through a couple of M6 overhangs, he continued up for 25m of vertical ice that averaged about 2cm thick, with only 2 knifeblades below him, and no opportunity for further protection!  With laser-like focus, he slowly tapped and tested his picks in the verglas (which he thought would be little thicker), shook out his pump, and forged on.  Fortunately thin ice was his specialty and despite the x-rating and extreme intensity, he was in his element.  I honestly don’t think many others could have pulled off such a lead, and following it, I often found myself hanging just from the first tooth of my picks.  I led a short pitch above his anchor, but with darkness closing in and another wild and committing bit of climbing above, I had to build an anchor and lower off, ending our attempt.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Ice-Rich@Storm%20Creek.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Rich Marshall attemping the route circa 2004 &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
That day entrenched itself in my memorey.  I’ve been back to that part of the Storm Creek headwall a few times over the years since, always interested to see what that sector of the wasll was looking like, but never saw the buttress ice up enough to look inviting again.  Cold snaps likely cause the early season ice to delaminate and then it just doesn&#039;t reform, hence, this is really a late fall to early winter route, and perhaps one that only occationaly comes in.  One wseek ago, however, Michelle and I were hoping to climb something in the area, but unseasonally warm temperatures made being below any steep or thin ice too dangerous, so our day turned out to be nothing more than hiking and scoping.  We ventured far enough up valley to see that more ice was dripping down the dream line than I had ever imagined, and upon returning to the valley, it dominated my thoughts for the following week.  Luckily Marc-Andre Leclerc was heading to the Rockies for the first time and was keen to get out, and I figured it would be great first route for us to climb together, as well as perfect intro to the Rockies for him, as he is known to have a solid head for intense climbing, and power to spare.   And I say luckily because the Banff Film festival was responsible for tying up most of my other partners who I would normally try to recruit for such an outing.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Upon getting to the base of the route, Marc immediately arranged rock rack on his harness, so instead of the usual rock paper scissors for first lead, I offered it to him as he seamed so keen.  Two options presented themselves and he chose the left one, a shallow right facing corner with a bit of ice dripping down it and small icicles decorating the wall around it dangling like christmas tree ornaments.  The climbing was steep and thin, and long technical moves were common.  The protection was tricky too, and Marc moved slowly but confidently, and made steady upward progress, never knowing where the next hold or piece of protection would appear.  A cruxy pull over the roof on 1-2 cm thick ice followed by a fun iced up handcrack and a good ledge to belay at.  It was definitely the best first lead in the Rockies I’ve ever witnessed!  Three out of the 4 pitons he placed were left fixed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p1low.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Marc near the beginning of the first pitch&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p1mid.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Marc setting up to pull the roof on the first pitch&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p1hi.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Here Marc is trying to get his tools established in ice that mostly falls apart when weighted &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The next pitch was pure fun, and I was psyched to get this one as this type of climbing is always special to me - steep, thin ice climbing with most of the gear in the rock!  I was surprised to pass the old anchor from ten years ago that I had built, as I thought we might have been further right, but it gave me a good boost of inspiration to have joined out original line, and I felt determined to finish the business.   From a stance at the top of strange fin like pillar of rock, an anemic ice pillar guarded the crux and the weakness through the overhanging wall.  I climbed delicately to its front, and pounded a knifeblade into a seam to its left, preparing mentally for some very engaging climbing above.   But then I noticed an suspicious, yet inviting foot-hold to my left, right on the crest of the arete.  I stepped over to it, and saw a I could turn the corner, and traverse into some ice runnels of better, less fragile and more protectable terrain that led to the same place.  Once in the runnels, my pace picked up and I made it to a perfect belay ledge with good cracks for an anchor, just as I ran out of rope.  As Marc neared the station, he asked if all climbing in the Rockies was this good, and I had to apologize for spoiling him on his first route, as this was about as good as it gets!   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p2low.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Me, on some very fun ice climbing near the start of the second pitch. Photo by Marc-Andre Leclerc &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p2hi.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Marc nearing the top of pitch 2.  This bit reminded of some of the climbing I did in Scotland last February. &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
He easily dispatched the last pitch of grade 4 ice, and we were soon on our way to down, stoked, and talking about more possibilities in the upcoming weeks.  Although the difficulties of this route weren’t too hard on top rope for the seconder, leading the first two pitches and following them were completely different things, and the intensity and seriousness far exceeded the technical levels of the climbing.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/p3.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Marc leading pitch 3 as it begins to snow lightly.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For me personally, it was awesome to have shared Marc’s first experience in the Rockies in this way, and to have finished an old project - one I dreampt about for so many years.  It was also an amazing feeling to have walked up to a line such as this, and to have completed it first try without placing any bolts.  We did carry a bolt kit in the pack, but fortunately that was where it stayed.  I think it’s pretty obvious from what’s written here, that this line comes highly recommended to those who like the style of proper traditional mixed, in a wild setting :) &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Approach notes:  It took us 3 hours to hike from the Stanley Headwall parking lot in ankle-deep snow, that became knee-deep closer to the route.  The climb is about halfway along the Storm Creek headwall and just right of The Peach, which is the route up big hanging icicles in the photo.  We used an exposed snow ramp that came in from the right to get to the start of the first pitch, and reversed it after two long rappels from the top of the climb.  Do not consider going here in times of high avalanche hazard!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 1:  40m M7.  Traverse easily left from the belay, then make steep moves to gain a shallow right facing corner that leads to a roof.  We left two peckers and a knifeblade fixed in the corner.  Move left through the roof to gain a good crack that trends back right to a belay ledge with many good anchor options.  The gear on this pitch is a little bit un-obvious but seemed adequate.  Having the three fixed pieces should help…&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 2: 60m WI6.  Work through ice blobs and mushrooms, past an old anchor (we used this for rappelling), to stance below an overhang.  Delicate moves up and left past some delicate ice, then around the arete on good holds, gain ice filled grooves  that lead to an excellent ledge with a good cracks for an anchor a few meters left of the main ice flow.  Most of the protection was in the rock, although I did place 6 ice screws as well.  This pitch was 90% ice, and 10% rock moves, although we felt like just an ice-grade was more appropriate.  The WI6 grade is a definitely more for the technical difficulties then the pump, and harder than your average pitch of “fat” WI6…&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 3.  20m WI4.  Vertical for a bit, then easier.  This pitch could vary in difficulty depending on the thickness of the ice.  A fixed rock anchor of two stoppers is just beyond the end of the ice.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rack beta:  We had a double set of cams from tips to #2 camelot, one #3, and one #4 camelot.  Doubles from tips to .75 camelot was nice, but singles from #1 to #4 would suffice.  A few pitons, nuts, and a half-dozen screws in the 10-13 cm range would be enough in the same conditions.  14 quick draws wasn’t quite enough for the long second pitch and I was wishing I had a couple more… 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/ice_mixed_climbing_0">Ice / mixed climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/kootenay_national_park_bc">Kootenay National Park B.C.</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/storm_creek_headwall">Storm Creek Headwall</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2014 00:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">114 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Blue Jeans</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2014/09/15/blue_jeans</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Josh Wharton and I must&#039;ve used up our luck and good weather on his last two highly productive visits, because we just got pretty much shut down on all things alpine we were interested in.  During the exact same dates as a year ago, we enjoyed a successful and rare repeat of the North Twin&#039;s Tower, while freezing levels remanied close to 4000m, and valley temps crested the 30 degree mark.  This year, four out of the 7.5 days we just spent together were full winter days with relatively large amounts of snowfall, all the way to the valley, that firmly slammed the door on everything we hoped to do.  We still drove many hundreds of kilometers trying to stay optimistic and psyched, but in the end, we had to settle for a warm-up day at Acephale (our favorite Bow Valley crag) before the apocolyptic weather began, and two days on Yamnuska working a 5.13 multi-pitch sport climb called Blue Jeans.  It&#039;s not that there wasn&#039;t alpine objectives that would&#039;ve been doable and perhaps enjoyable, we&#039;re just picky and like to stay focused on harder technical routes whenever possible. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Blue Jeans has only had one proper repeat (by Vikki Weldon) since it&#039;s first ascent four years ago (by Derek Galloway), and Josh was psyched to make the third.  The highly technical climbing made quick redpointing a difficult propositon though, and it turned out that a mere two days wouldn&#039;t be enough to figure out the beta, and then link all the moves of the two crux pitches.  Anyways, it was fun trying and a bit more effort next year will be needed for success. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Perhaps the most memorable part of the Blue Jeans adventure was the amount of snow we had to plough through just to get to it - thigh deep at times!!!   Normally it would take an hour of hiking, although with all the fresh snow, it took over two hours on our first try, and it was -9 degrees Celcius at the car park when we left!  Then in full sun, it was so hot on the rock that it felt hard to stick to the steep limestone.  A couple days later, our apprach time was cut in half thanks to the trail being in, and some cloud cover greatly improved the friction.  The first three pitches cruised by, but the fourth was the end of the redpoint attempt.  Josh came close, but in the end we retreated.  Here&#039;s a few pics:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7262.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the approach trail.  Had someone not hiked three quarters of the way the day before, we wouldn&#039;t have made it
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7268.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7272.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh following the first pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7305.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh onsighting the second pitch  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7282.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh starting the third pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7335.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh on the fourth pitch 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/rock_climbing">Rock climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/yamnuska">Yamnuska</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2014 00:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">113 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>East Creek</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2014/08/14/east_creek_0</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Michelle Kadatz, Paul Bride and I flew in a heli into East Creek (the West side of the Bugaboos) for a few days last week.  Paul was psyched to shoot landscape photos while Michelle and I checked out some of the incredible rock in the Pigeon feathers.  Although there are quite a few routes here described in the guidebook, the Pigeon Feathers remain a slightly more obscure corner of the Bugs, despite their amazing quality, and proximity to a great camp.  Upon landing, we hiked around until we found something that was really inspiring - some unclimbed splitters on Wide Awake Tower, slightly right of the original Wide Awake route.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Wide Awake Tower.  Our route starts part way up the snow gully.  photo: Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On our first climbing day under stormy skies, we made it nearly three quarters of the way up before the skies started unleashing thunder and lightning.  Going down was the only option.  While pulling the ropes after the first rappel, a toaster sized block popped off and landed right in the pile of rope that was stacking itself in front of us as it fell.  The result was both lead and tag lines were chopped in the middle!  The storm intensified and we had no choice but to hunker down in a chimney, while rain, hail, and a lot of very close thunder and lightning came down all around us.  Backs against the wall and all the metal off the harnesses, we slowly got colder and wetter.  Multiple rounds of this continued until finally it passed and we made it down to the glacier safely.  By the time we were walking back to camp, it was nice and sunny so we lapped the first three pitches of the classic Solitary Confinement.  It was great to get back on this one again as it had been 8 or 9 years since I had climbed it, and it was one Michelle wanted to do too.   Our thirty-five meter rope was exactly what it took to get to the first anchor of this amazing 5.11 continuous crack that gradually expanded from tips to off-width over three pitches.  With only two #4 camelots, the even wider 4th pitch wasn’t really an option, which was fine by me.  Three 4&#039;s, and three 5&#039;s would be considerated adequate for it...
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0176.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle on Pitch 3 of Solitary Confinement.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following day we hiked to Applebee where it was possible to get two more ropes, which took the better part of the day via the Bugaboo Glacier.  On day 3 we got back to work on what we were now calling Electric Funeral, obviously a reference to a Black Sabbath song, and our experience on it the first day.  Paul and I are both huge Black Sabbath fans and when we get together, Sabbath becomes our theme.  Michelle didn’t know the song, but liked the name!  The climbing went well, although seventh pitch took getting dead-ended on two other option before I finally figured out what to do.  Not comfortable with the run-out traverse to a grassy crack, I pendulummed across the face to the seam, then went into aid / cleaning mode with a nut tool and wire brush.  By the time I got to the next ledge, I was so psyched to come back to send the pitch, as well as the amazing looking splitter above that bee-lined for the summit.  It was cold, windy and getting late so we decided to save it for the next day.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Playing with fire at camp. Wide awake is the rightmost tower in the background  photo: Paul Bride 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On Day 4 the weather was looking pretty bad, and confidence of being able to complete the project was low.  However, we were back, and for the first time we brought the power drill and enough bolts to set up some stations.  We were psyched to have gone through the process a couple of times without bolts, and felt like the route was worthy of setting up to attract more climber to enjoy its quality.  Fortunately the weather held and even got pretty nice, although quite windy in the afternoon.  On pitch 7, I led out to a small foot ledge and placed the only protection bolt as high above my head as I could, then lowered the drill back to the belay and continured sending the pitch, which was delightfully sustained and interesting to climb.  It was more like face climbing with a thin crack for protection, than the typical crack climbing that’s far more common in the area.  The crux came right off the belay on the pitch 8 while laybacking off amazing chicken heads to pull a small roof!  Trending right, beautiful cracks and transfer moves continued, and the rope was nearly used up before finally reaching a good stance.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle following the 7th pitch  photo Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-12.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW on pich 8, gunning for the top  photo Paul Bride 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sweet views from the summit and a smooth rappel had us celebrating back in camp before long.  Our time was up and we had the heavy, half-day slog / half-day drive home to look forward to the next day.  It had been a fun process exploring this obscure conner of the Bugs and I know I’ll be back again.  The crack system immediately left - aka Wide Awake, looked amazing!  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-5.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Almost at the belay at the top of pitch 5.  It&#039;s the triangular ledge a body length to my right.  Photo Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-7.jpg&quot; /&gt; Michelle bringing me accross the traverse of Pitch 4.  Photo Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0226.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle on pitch 6. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0231.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle leading pitch 3  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0235.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle following pitch 7
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0242.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW starting up pitch 8, photo Michelle Kadatz 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0244.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW passing some perched flakes and the chimney on the way to the summit.  Photo Michelle Kadatz 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Electric Funeral, 300m, 5.11+,  FA: Michelle Kadatz and Jon Walsh, August 7th 2014&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A fun route on great rock, highly recommended, and it’s easily scoped from nearby snow slopes.  Pitches 7 and 8 are nothing short of spectacular!  The route is straightforward to rappel, or to walk off.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rack: 1 full set of stoppers.  10 - 12 draws.  Double set of cams from purple C3 or red X4 to #3 camelot. One #4 camelot and one #5 camelot are nice for the short wide sections of pitches 2 and 3.  If the plan is to rappel, the #4 and 5 came lots can be left at the top of pitch 3.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Approach: Start up a the snowgully to the right of the tower&#039;s &amp;quot;nose&amp;quot; and ascend snow for about 80 meters.  Look for a distint left facing corner that leads to a righ faceing corner that make up pitches 2 nd 3.  We climbed a body length of 5.7 and then a 5 meter traverse left of easy 5th class to get a good belay ledge where you can dump your packs and get organised.  This is directly below the changing corners of pitches 2 and 3.  We left a cairn here... 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
P1:  5.10-, 30 meters; climb through bulge from belay and trend left to a left facing corner.  A couple of balance moves to gets you to a crack that leads back right to a left facing corner with two wide cracks in it, and a two bolt belay station. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P2: 5.10, 20 meters; Climb the obvious wide cracks above up the left facing corner to a good ledge, and a gear belay (takes camelots .5, .75, 1)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P3: 5.10, 20 meters;  A few off-width moves give way to nice hand-jamming.  Belay at a good ledge with a huge, easily slung horn for the belay.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P4: 5.9, 50 meters; climb a short bulge above the belay and make a rising traverse to the right, until a short down climb becomes necessary.  Climb down a few meters, then back up to a good belay ledge.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P5: 5.10+, 50 meters; Great hand and finger cracks head up and slightly left.  Belay at a small but comfortable ledge below an overlap. A very nice pitch. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P6: 5.10+, 15 meters.  Pull through the overlap and up a short groove.  Rather than continue up the dirt right facing corner, make face moves out left onto the exposed / featured / golden face and up to a two bolt belay at a small ledge. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P7: 5.11-, 30 meters; Face climb up and left past a bolt, to gain a thin crack that leads straight up towards a roof.  Two bolt belay below roof at small ledge. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P8: 5.11+ 50 meters; A crux roof sequence leads to spectacular crack climbing that trends rightwards towards the summit, sometimes transferring from crack-to-crack, one of such transfers providing a second, slightly easier crux!   A two bolt belay at a good stance comes after 50 meters&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
P9: 5.9, 20 meters;  A short straightforward pitch passes a chimney, and gets you to the summit.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rappel notes: easy down-climbing about 5-meters off the summit to a slung block is required to get back to the last belay.  A 25-meter rappel straight down from there (the last bolted station) gets you to another bolted station on a ledge that wasn’t part of the route.  It would be possible to climb over to this on pitch 8, although this wasn’t done on the first ascent.  A 50-meter rappel from here gets you to the bolted belay between pitch 6 and 7.  Then 50-meters to a slung horn you passed near the start of P5.  Two single rope rappels on slung horns throughout the owed angle traverse section, get you to the top of pitch 3.  Then a double rope rappel easily makes the top of P1…     &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/bugaboos">Bugaboos</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2014 04:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">112 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Gripped Cover</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2014/02/15/gripped_cover</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Gripped16i1_tearsheets_OFC.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This fine image taken by &lt;a href=&quot;http://paulbride.com/&quot;&gt;Paul Bride&lt;/a&gt; has just appeared on the cover&lt;a href=&quot;http://gripped.com/&quot;&gt; Gripped Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.  I&#039;m stoked and honored to be featured on the cover!!!  It&#039;s the first pitch of the classic &lt;i&gt;Nightmare on Wolf Street&lt;/i&gt;, on the Stanley Headwall. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/ice_mixed_climbing_0">Ice / mixed climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 21:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">110 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The BMC winter meet and Scottish mixed madness</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2014/02/12/the_bmc_winter_meet_and_scottish_mixed_madness</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
&lt;!--
/* Font Definitions */
@font-face
{font-family:Cambria;
panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;
mso-font-charset:0;
mso-generic-font-family:auto;
mso-font-pitch:variable;
mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;}
/* Style Definitions */
p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal
{mso-style-parent:&quot;&quot;;
margin-top:0cm;
margin-right:0cm;
margin-bottom:10.0pt;
margin-left:0cm;
mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
font-size:12.0pt;
font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;
mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-fareast-font-family:Cambria;
mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;
mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-bidi-font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}
@page Section1
{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;
margin:72.0pt 90.0pt 72.0pt 90.0pt;
mso-header-margin:36.0pt;
mso-footer-margin:36.0pt;
mso-paper-source:0;}
div.Section1
{page:Section1;}
--&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;The BMC winter meet and winter climbing in the
Scottish Highlands trip report&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/ExtasyApproach.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW approaching Extacy.  The route goes up just right of the dangling icicles. &lt;i&gt; Photo Nick Bullock  &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
&lt;!--
/* Font Definitions */
@font-face
{font-family:Cambria;
panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;
mso-font-charset:0;
mso-generic-font-family:auto;
mso-font-pitch:variable;
mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;}
/* Style Definitions */
p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal
{mso-style-parent:&quot;&quot;;
margin-top:0cm;
margin-right:0cm;
margin-bottom:10.0pt;
margin-left:0cm;
mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
font-size:12.0pt;
font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;
mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-fareast-font-family:Cambria;
mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;
mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-bidi-font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}
@page Section1
{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;
margin:72.0pt 90.0pt 72.0pt 90.0pt;
mso-header-margin:36.0pt;
mso-footer-margin:36.0pt;
mso-paper-source:0;}
div.Section1
{page:Section1;}
--&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
&lt;!--
/* Font Definitions */
@font-face
{font-family:Cambria;
panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;
mso-font-charset:0;
mso-generic-font-family:auto;
mso-font-pitch:variable;
mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;}
/* Style Definitions */
p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal
{mso-style-parent:&quot;&quot;;
margin-top:0cm;
margin-right:0cm;
margin-bottom:10.0pt;
margin-left:0cm;
mso-pagination:widow-orphan;
font-size:12.0pt;
font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;
mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-fareast-font-family:Cambria;
mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;
mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;
mso-bidi-font-family:&quot;Times New Roman&quot;;
mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;}
@page Section1
{size:612.0pt 792.0pt;
margin:72.0pt 90.0pt 72.0pt 90.0pt;
mso-header-margin:36.0pt;
mso-footer-margin:36.0pt;
mso-paper-source:0;}
div.Section1
{page:Section1;}
--&gt;
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;I’m just back from what will likely be my biggest
adventure of the 2013 / 2014 winter season – a visit to the Scottish Highlands
to sample their unique flavor of mixed climbing.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Scotland had been calling&lt;span&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;In Scotland, the traditional approach to climbing is
strongly maintained and the history of the climbs is well remembered.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Modern ice climbing was in fact developed
here, and early prototypes by Chouinard and others were tested on the walls of Ben
Nevis and surrounding area. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;I was fortunate enough to attend the 2014 BMC
Winter Meet this year, with my girlfriend Michelle Kadatz, where 47 foreign climbers
from 25 countries got together at the Glenmore Lodge in Aviemore during the
last week of January.&lt;span&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;Every
day, each visitor gets paired up with a host climber from the UK, familiar with
the Scottish winter climbing scene, and together they head out on an adventure.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;At the end of the day, everybody has
dinner and drinks together, and has the option to watch slideshows and
presentations at the lodge’s lecture theater.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Halfway through the week, a partner switch is made so the
visitor gets a total of two different hosts to climb with.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Conditions throughout the week were tricky with
an unusual amount of snow, a high avalanche hazard and generally bad
weather.&lt;span&gt;   &lt;/span&gt;This however seemed
to force people to dig a little deeper, and as a result, there were a lot of
early starts made and an impressive list of climbs got done.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/ExtasyP1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Extacy pitch 1 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;My first partner was Nick Bullock, a veteran of
the Scottish winter scene, who had been putting up cutting edge first ascents
and generally raising the bar for well over a decade, both in Scotland and in
the greater ranges.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Like me, he
really liked to get after it.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;But
in order to do just that, it seemed prudent to use our first day, a bad weather
day even by Scottish standards, to put a track into Craeg Meagaidh and try to
find the start of a route called Extasy, put up during the 2005 winter meet by
Bruno Sourzac and Dave Hesleden.&lt;span&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;It had been one Nick was stoked for since a friend of his made the only
repeat and spoke highly of its quality.&lt;span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;That day we couldn’t see more than halfway up the 250m face, but with
the boot track in and the start of the route located, the cards seemed nicely stacked
in our favor. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;The hike was also a
good way to shake off my jetlag. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;We made the routes 3&lt;sup&gt;rd&lt;/sup&gt; ascent the next day in a
17-hour car-to-car effort, and it didn’t disappoint.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The entire cliff was coated in thin ice and rime – prime
Scottish conditions, and the climbing was fiercely sustained!&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Following the thickest, most supportive
ice or neve, usually just a couple of centimeters thick and often too thin to
hold body weight, we battled upwards for 5 long pitches.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;It never felt like we had the route in
the bag until the very top.&lt;span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;Protection was scarce, and head-spinning run-outs were the norm.&lt;span&gt;  A perfect intro!  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Nick stated on his blog:&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;“&lt;/span&gt;Its difficult to imaging that I
will have a more compelling, engaging day of the winter than this
one. We climbed the route totally on ice but the ice was less than perfect
and the ground at times was steep. The gear to protect the climb was minimal
and the descent ‘interesting’… All in all, a pretty full-on day.”&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Extasy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Extacy - Nick climbing pitch 2.  The route snaked it&#039;s way around and through many steep bits
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Extasy2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Nick leading off on pitch 4, hoping to find a groove jst a little more left.  It was now storming.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/ExtasyP5.jpg&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
JW leading the start of pitch 5.  Headlamp ready, just in case!  Fortunately I completed this 62 m pitch before turning it on.  &lt;i&gt;photo: Nick Bullock  &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;The next day, the weather was the usual
slashing rain in the valley bottoms and winds up to 90 mph up high. This made
it easier to take a much needed rest day, as Extasy had taxed our bodies both
mentally and physically. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;The event
organizers initiated a partner switch that night, and I got paired with Greg
Boswell.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Greg is as bad-ass as
they come and has been turning heads both at home, and abroad, with lots of
difficult and serious new routes and repeats under his belt.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;We immediately started making plans to
climb a new line he had scoped on the beautiful quartzite walls of Beinn Eighe.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;But Nick’s new partner needed a rest
day so he insisted on making joining us too. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/BeinEigheSummitRidge.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Greg Boswell and I on the summit of Beinn Eighe, before rappelling into the West-central gully.  This was by far the best weather day of the trip.  &lt;i&gt;photo: Nick Bullock &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;After a couple hours of approaching, we reached
the base of the route.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Greg won
the first rock paper scissors and fired a series of roofs above a snow ledge
near the top of the West-central Gully.&lt;span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;Much to Nick’s dismay I won the second rock paper scissors and scored
the second pitch - a long slightly overhanging off-width with a thin coating of
verglas.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Fortunately the rock had
just enough other features, and it turned out to be one of the best pitches I
climbed during the trip.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Nick
fired the final crack / corner system and we were soon treated to amazing
sunset over a stunning view of the north-western highlands.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;“Lochs” dotted the green valleys
everywhere and the snowline at mid height gave the mountains a bigger feel,
despite their low altitudes.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot;&gt;
Nick wrote on his blog: “The perfect day. Stunning settled
weather, a magnificent situation and a line both Greg and I had spotted a few
years back. I lost Scissor, paper, stone all-day and climbed the third
pitch, which was still good but not as spectacular as the second pitch or as
sustained as the first pitch. We called it Making the Cut after talking to
Simon Richardson about the amount of entries he has on his blog Scottish
Winter climbs.”
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MakingtheCutP1(2).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Greg hooking his way out some sweet quartzite roofs and pitch 1   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MakingtheCutP1.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Another angle of Greg on pitch 1.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MakingtheCutP2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Working my way up the sustained chimney, off-width, corner - pitch 2 of Making the Cut.   &lt;i&gt;photo: Greg Boswell &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Two days later, we were hoping to do another
route on the same face, but after an hour of sitting in the car hoping for the
winds and rain to calm down, we opted for plan b.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;This time it was Nick and I (Greg’s knee strain was acting
up, and he was getting off treatment) and Michelle and her partner Ian
Parnell.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Two days earlier they had
a big success on a 9-pitch Ben Nevis route called the Centurion one of the
longest in the area.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Another
nearby peak called Mael Gorm offered “the shortest approach in Scotland” which
by the time we got there made sense, especially with the gale force wind gusts.
&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Although not quite as spectacular
as the first two climbs, it was a popular spot that day and many routes saw climbers
on them, and certainly way better than festering at the lodge.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Back at the Meet that night, wine flowed freely
as everyone celebrated an amazing week. &lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The energy had been incredible and it had a been a long
time since I’d seen so many really passionate mixed climbers getting after it
like that. For both myself and Michelle (who had amassed a route list most
locals were jealous of), there couldn’t have been a better introduction to winter
climbing in Scotland, and we’re deeply thankful to the BMC for organizing it,
our UK hosts – especially Nick, Greg, Will and Ian, and from the support we
received from the Alpine Club of Canada and Arcteryx for helping making it all
happen.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MegaRouteX.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Mega Route X.  Looks almost like a pure ice route, but it had some intesting mixed sections on the second pitch. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Now it was time to get after it on our own, and
our photographer friend Paul Bride had just flown over from Squamish B.C. to
join us.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Scotland had been on his
bucket list for a long time, and he was psyched to tag along to shoot some
climbing.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;However, the weather
wasn’t panning out very well, and we got shut down a two days in a row, and not
for lack of trying.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;At least we
managed to tour the countryside a bit and sample some of the finer local
vintages.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The folks that live in
the hills were incredibly hospitable and easy to get along with.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Finally we got some weather decent
enough for climbing, and we headed up the Number 3 gully on Ben Nevis, home to
some famous test-pieces I was hoping to try.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;A thick fog on its upper reaches forced us to stay on lower
cliffs, and we climbed some obvious thin ice lines called Mega Route X, which
is classic, and a wild overhanging dagger line called Feeding Frenzy.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Late in the afternoon it cleared enough
to see the crazy looking rime plastered to some of the higher walls.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MegaRouteX(2).jpg&quot; /&gt;Mega Route X, a thin classic. Mega Fun!  &lt;i&gt;Photo: Paul Bride   &lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;We descended to the town of Fort Williams,
hoping to get another chance.&lt;span&gt;  
&lt;/span&gt;Two more horrendously bad weather days passed, although on the second,
we hiked through the slashing rain to the deluxe CIC hut at the base of the Ben’s
North Face.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The forecast called
for “a rare benign day” on Friday, which didn’t exactly pan out, as the fog
level again was much too low to climb at the higher routes with the thick
rime.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Maybe it was just as well as
the avalanche hazard was still high and we observed a number of fresh fracture
lines a few days earlier.&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/scotlandblog(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
Tea time, with the Ben Nevis bible.  Michelle enjoying life in the CIC hut 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/scotlandblog%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/scotlandblog%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Eventually we settled on trying a route that seemed
to be unclimbed, just left of Mick Fowler’s 7-pitch classic – The Shield
Direct.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;After two-and-a-half
pitches of sustained overhanging dihedral action, laced with thin ice and neve,
we merged back with the shield and continued up it to the top of pitch-4.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The benign weather was abruptly ended
with strong winds, which turned the route into a river of spindrift, making
upward progress virtually impossible.&lt;span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;But the pitches had been wild ones and the beast within was fed. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/SheildVariationP1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
The start of the variation. &lt;i&gt; Photo Paul Bride &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/SheildVariationP2.jpg&quot; /&gt; And a little higher up.  &lt;i&gt;Photo: Paul Bride&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt;Scottish winter climbing is intense.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;Every pitch was a memorable battle that
had me focused on nothing but the present.&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;The Highlands truly are the quintessential real deal venue
for mixed adventure. &lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;Rich with
history and virtually devoid of any in-situ gear, proper mixed climbing in its
purest form was a refreshing experience!&lt;span&gt; 
&lt;/span&gt;The addictiveness of it grew on me throughout the trip, and I know it
won’t be long before I’m back again.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot; style=&quot;margin-bottom: 0.0001pt&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Helvetica&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 03:35:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">109 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The North Pillar</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/09/16/the_north_pillar</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
The North Pillar&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
There are less than a handful of people I know who have expressed interest in climbing the Twins Tower.  The ones that live within a day&#039;s drive were unavailable.  Not wanting to miss what I suspected were nothing less than exceptional conditions on the the North Pillar, thanks to a low snow year / hot summer, I went out on a limb and asked Josh Wharton if he had time and interest to give it a go with me.  I have to admit I was surprised when he said yes and immediately bought a Denver - Calgary plane ticket.  The alpine stars continued to align themselves as a perfect high pressure system settled into place as he stepped off the plane.  The next morning, we headed up the Icefield Parkway, and hiked over the Woolley Shoulder with light packs, expecting to have a food / fuel cache waiting for us when we got to the Lloyd McKay hut that Josh had left there in 2011.  A friend had confirmed it was looking good two weeks prior, and had even donated a few items to it.   Tragically, the latest entry in the hut logbook dated September the 1st said &amp;quot;thanks for the grub, Josh&amp;quot;, and only slim pickings were left of it.  As Josh&#039;s note in his bag had said he&#039;d be back in 2012, we could hardly blame anybody but ourselves that most of the bars and freeze dried dinners were missing, and accepted the fact that light and fast just got lighter and faster!  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The next morning we left the hut with 8 bars and 8 gels each, and a couple of recovery and electrolyte drink mixes as personal food.  For shared food, we had 6 packs of instant oats and couple hundred grams of granola + a small bag of trail mix that would be our breakfasts.  For dinners, we two Knorr soups packets (unfortunately onion flavoured), one pack of Threshold Provision Salmon jerky, and one 100g chocolate bar.  We also had 8 packets of Starbucks &amp;quot;Via&amp;quot; instant coffee!  It was about 5000 calories each, and we knew we&#039;d be spending at least the next two nights out (it turned out to be 3.5 days)!  Hiking back to the car for more supplies didn&#039;t make a lot of sense, so we just accepted the fact that we&#039;d be getting pretty hungry, and enjoyed carrying the lighter packs.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
On the second pitch Josh wasn&#039;t sure if he was psyched anymore, but accepted the fact that I didn&#039;t want to slog back out the way we came.  A lot of the climbing was chossy, and a lot of the gear was marginal, but there was just enough of it was good enough to continue pushing upwards.  We cursed the first ascentionists, both for not cleaning it better and for talking the route up so much!  It was mind boggling to us, that the only three parties to have climbed the face previously had done so in 1974, 1985, and in the winter of 2004.  All parties had been pushed to their mental and physical limits, including ourselves.  It seemed like we were right on the edge of our risk tolerance levels the entire time, and perhaps even crossed the line.  Staying on that edge for such an extended time was exhausting!   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The headwall turned out to be impressively steep and we began to haul the packs more than climb with them.  It was so steep in fact, that they often hauled cleanly without even touching the rock.  Fortunately the rock quality improved.  1985 5.10d - which many of the pitches were rated, seemed sandbagged to say the least.  Continuous crack systems, often connected by gymnastic face moves, led through vertical to overhanging terrain for 13 pitches, to a wild climax at the top.  With only about 15 meters left before hitting lower angled summit ridge, a few meters of straightforward aid climbing up a knifeblade seam had to done above a ledge, to gain a series of big, run-out jugs that traversed the lip of a big overhang!  It was the only aid on the entire route for us, and it would probably go free at 5.12-, however dangerous fall potential put risking the free ascent out of our reach (despite being both quite comfortable at that grade).  It was no place to be taking chances as retreat would be practically impossible at that point, especially with the state our ropes were in. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The rest of the route was fairly straight forward, but worked out, despite making a couple minor route-finding decision.  One was thinking we&#039;d save time and energy taking a short cut across the north face of Twins Tower right below the summit, in order to avoid some cornices, and the second was opting for the standard descent off of Mt. Cromwell to reach the valley, rather than hike across the Columbia Icefileds.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Climbing the Twin&#039;s Tower was in hindsight, a great and satisfying experience for both of us, despite not always being fun in the moment.  It would be hard to recommend it to anyone, although if you&#039;re really psyched for a huge physical and mental adventure, it could be as good a place as any!              &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Our conditions were absolutely perfect.  I don&#039;t think we saw a single cloud for the three days on the face, and maybe only a couple small ones on the fifth day.  Visibility was unlimited - On the summit we could see from Mt. Robson to the Bugaboos. Temperatures were perfect too, with reported freezing levels over 3500m the entire time, and there was virtually no natural rockfall, except in a couple of expected places like gullies below ice ledges.  Even there it was quite small, and mostly on the lower part of the route.   The rock was generally very dry.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Hardest route in the Rockies???  maybe…  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The itinerary we followed went like this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Monday, Sept. 9th: Leave car at 1 pm, arrive at the Alberta hut at 6&lt;br /&gt;
Sept. 10: Leave hut at 5 a.m., approach N. Twin.  By 10:30 we are finally belaying on the first pitch.  Arrive at bivi site on &amp;quot;ice ledge&amp;quot;, just below headwall at about 9 as it&#039;s getting dark.&lt;br /&gt;
Sept. 11: Climb 12 pitches of headwall and bivi one pitch below the top of it.  &lt;br /&gt;
Sept. 12: Climb last pitch of headwall, and the summit ridge above it.  Traverse a few meters below the double corniced summit ridge of the Twin&#039;s tower, and traverse the summit ridge of the North Twin (3731m).  Stand on the summit around 4ish.   Cross the Columbia Icefield toward to the Crommell / Stutfield col, and bivi slightly below it as it got dark. &lt;br /&gt;
Sept.13: Rappel and down-climb cliffs / hike out to the road which takes 6 hours.  Arrive at car at 3:30.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Summary:  Second ascent of the Twins Tower via the North Pillar - Josh Wharton, Jon Walsh Sept 10-12, 2013 (F.A.: Barry Blanchard / David Cheesmond 1985, 5.10d A2, 1500+meters from bergshrund to summit).   2013 grade: 5.11b r/x, A1 (about 4 meters of aid climbing) on the last pitch of the headwall.  I suppose the r/x grade is irrelevant, as what else would you expect getting on an alpine limestone face of this size?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_2035%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Sunrise on the Twins Tower and the line of our ascent.  &lt;i&gt;photo Josh Wharton&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_2055%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW on the headwall.  &lt;i&gt;photo Josh Wharton  &lt;/i&gt;    
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_2068%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
JW getting into mixed climbing onthe upper ridge.  &lt;i&gt;photo Josh Wharton&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_2078%20copy.jpg&quot; height=&quot;494&quot; width=&quot;686&quot; /&gt; On the summit of the North Twin. &lt;i&gt;photo Josh Wharton&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some of my B-roll:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh on pitch 2
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Packing after the first bivi
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-1-list-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(2).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking up at the headwall
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(3).jpg&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh&#039;s 1st block, pitch 4 of the headwall
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(4).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pitch 5
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(6).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pitch 9
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-5-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(7).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
the end of Pitch 10 on the Headwall
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(8).jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The morning after the second bivi. Coffee time! Yes we&amp;quot;slept&amp;quot; here!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-7-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(9).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Morning light on Mt. Alberta 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/twin(10).jpg&quot; height=&quot;427&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally above the headwall!  Only a few of hours of lower angled terrain to the top 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2013 03:16:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">108 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Spirits of Asgard</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/08/12/spirits_of_asgard</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
It&#039;s been a busy summer as always and I&#039;m getting behind on updating this blog.  About six weeks ago, the video &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/70149174&quot;&gt;Spirits of Asgard&lt;/a&gt; was released, and has been very well received.  It&#039;s been posted to Outside Television, as well as received a Vimeo Staff pick, so it&#039;s recieved a lot of views, which is pretty cool!  A huge congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualavigne.com/&quot;&gt;Joshua Lavigne&lt;/a&gt; for producing it.  Check his website for more photos of the trip as well as the July / August 2013 issue of Gripped which features some pics and a 2500 word story I wrote about it.  Josh&#039;s words and images are also shared in the 2013 Canadian Alpine Journal.  Although the video covers the &amp;quot;darker&amp;quot; aspects of our trip, such as a couple of close calls we had, it was very a fun and successful trip.  Some photos and stories have been shared here on a blog post from last August, but I thought I&#039;d take a few a minutes to share a few more images as I link the the video here, as an attempt to share a greater visual tour of the amazing landscape Baffin has to offer.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/70149174?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=999999&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;411&quot; width=&quot;730&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/70149174&quot;&gt;Spirits of Ásgarðr&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/arcteryx&quot;&gt;ARC&#039;TERYX&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimeo.com&quot;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Asgard.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The north side of Mt. Asgard and the reason for going here.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines168.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ines and Josh enjoying perfect weather and spectacular views on the 60km approach.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines162.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One of the many stream crossings
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines160.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sunrise at Summit Lake
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines158.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We were always hungry! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines155.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A cariboo skull and atlers on the Turner Glacier, and the first views of the 1200m high North Face of Mt. Asgard  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines145.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Getting up the Turner Gl. required a lot of stream hopping, which sometimes required following them for a long ways before finding the easiest spot to jump.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines133.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Base camp on the turner.  Asgard peaking through the clouds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-7-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines132.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our kitchen and living room for about a week 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines116.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ines getting started up the incredible south Buttress of Mt. Loki
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines114.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Smiles on the summit of Loki
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines67.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Getting high on Asgard. Mt. Loki is the highest rock peak accross the glacier and our base camp is on the strip of rock, directly below its summit.  Photo by Joshua Lavigne
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines66.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh and Ines folllow yet another pitch of perfect splitters
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines51.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh getting western, a couple ofpitches below the summit 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Baffin_Ines96.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ines at base camp below Asgard. 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/baffin">Baffin</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 23:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">107 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bow Valley Rock</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/07/20/bow_valley_rock</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Rock climbing in the Bow Valley has been so much fun lately, and although I&#039;ve been mostly seasoning single pitch sport climbs at Bataan and Lake Louise, I&#039;ve been really stoked on a couple of multi-pitch lines I&#039;ve recently done.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Super Mega-Fauna (named after an encounter with a bear on the trail) was put up a few years back by the late, great Dave Thompson.  Dave was one of the legendary route setters of the BV and this route is a prime example of his amazing drive.  Sustained, technical, well bolted, and perched just above tree line ousted of Banff, it&#039;s a perfect route for summer.  8 pitches up the NE face of Mt. Edith and it definitely gets my recommendation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MtEdith10.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle Kadatz on Super Mega-Fauna
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MtEdith2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The NE face of Mt. Edith.  SMF goes right up the middle of it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/MtEdith15.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Michelle halfway up the route 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another awesome line I climbed by another of the BV&#039;s best route setters is Silent Auction.  Greg Tos opened this one up just a few months ago, and with five pitches of 5.12-, three of 5.11 and one of 5.10, this has to be one of the most sustained at its grade in the area.  Highly recommended!  Although it was sunny the day we climbed, there had been quite a bit of rain the week before, and we found the crux holds on the second and fourth pitches to be a little damp.  Unfortunately the damp holds prevented us from getting the on-sight, on those pitches, but otherwise, we both managed to on-sight the rest of the route. There is so much good looking stone in this giant grotto on Grotto mountain just outside of Canmore, that I can only imagine this is perhaps the start of a stellar future climbing zone!   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minaret5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Samuel lambert on the 3rd pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minaret6.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sam following the 4th pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minaret8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking accross and all the unclimbed rock!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot; 	 http://alpinestyle.ca/sites/default/files/Minaret13.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;p&gt;
Sam following the wildly overhanging 6th pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minaret14.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nice water streaks on the 7th pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Minaret17.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sam locking into a knee bar on the 9th pitch, and getting the first bit of sun of the day at around 3:30 in the afternoon.  Climbing the whole route in the shade on a warm day made for perfect conditions.  We both climbed every pitch pitch in a t-shirt, and hauled a light bag with a light puffy jacket each for the belays.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I write this, I&#039;m only a few hours away from my second trip into the Bugaboos this summer.  So Stoked!!!  The first trip was amazing with adventures on the Minaret Tower and amongst the Pigeon Feathers, and no doubt the second one will be super fun too.   I&#039;ll post some pics when I&#039;m back in August...  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/rock_climbing">Rock climbing</category>
 <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2013 13:37:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">106 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Spring skiing</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/06/13/spring_skiing</link>
 <description>&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Lefroy1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin Haley climbing the West face of Mt. Lefroy, with views into the Lake O&#039;hara basin and beyond 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Often in May, I focus a lot of my playtime on skiing some of the bigger alpine lines the Rockies has to offer.  The inspiration I find in this range seems to be unlimited, and having my psyched friends Colin Haley and Ptor Spricenieks around increased the stoke even more.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Conditions this year were tricky though.  A drought with summer-like temps at the beginning of May, followed by mixed weather with very little precip or good overnight freezes was the grim reality we had to work with.  This combo made it tricky to get as much done as we hoped, but we still managed.  I&#039;ve generally been patient, and skied a lot of steep lines in powdery conditions.  But the reality is, that often when snow sticks to icy north faces, the sun quickly changes the surface of it to something else.   With snowpack and surface conditions going through constant change, the temperatures need to be carefully monitored. Timing needs to be calculated for both safety, success, and for maximum pleasure.  Getting the goods in prime conditions requires some luck perhaps, but definitely a lot of forethought.  The snow finally came near the end of the month, and on the 26th of May, we got lucky and skied Mt. Temple from it&#039;s summit it amazing conditions.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So here are some photos, from various roadside adventures May adventures.  Hopefully the captions tell enough of the story.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also worth checking out are two links to G3&#039;s blog, from some crucial late April shredding.  They are the stories and photos from very memorable days I had on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.genuineguidegear.com/life/blog/jonwalsh/fine-line-sweet-summit&quot;&gt;Mt. Burgess&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.genuineguidegear.com/life/blog/jonwalsh/ticking-classic-steeps-mt-stanley&quot;&gt;Mt. Stanley&lt;/a&gt;.  I believe the NW couloir on Mt. Burgess was probably a first descent, and hopefully a video from that day will be linked here soon. The day on Stanley was super memorable for the fantastic conditions and ultra-classics I finally got around to&amp;quot;ticking&amp;quot;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Lefroy11.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the West summit of Lefroy.  The main summit, about two meters higher is about 50 meters behind us, and garded by some ripe cornices we weren&#039;t interested in climbing accross.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Lefroy13.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin shredding  chunky corn  on the West Face of Mt. Lefroy, with the classic East face of Victoria in the background 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0147.JPG&quot; /&gt;JW, climbing the East face of Mt. Victoria, but un-inspiring snow conditions and warm temps had us turning around about 500 meters below the summit.  Photo:Colin Haley 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Lefroy35.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A couple hours later, we had recovered a stashed pack of rock climbing gear and were enjoying perfect climbing conditions at the Back of the Lake.  Two feet of snow on the ground and shirts-off conditions all day, even while belaying!  We managed 6 pitches of rock and over 4000&#039; of skiing.  Multi-sport at it&#039;s finest! Colin, warming up on Wicked Gravity
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn260.jpg&quot; /&gt;Next up was the Silverhorn, the peak to the right of Athabasca, and the ski line is the sun shadow line right of center.  Unfortunately a wind slab turned us around about half way up, but better safe than sorry.  At least it still yielded some good turns.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident,Skyladder37.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ptor brewing coffee at a campground in the wee hours before the attempt 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn246.jpg&quot; /&gt;Colin and Ptor touring up the glacier
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn248.jpg&quot; /&gt; Kicking Steps
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn249.jpg&quot; /&gt; Ptor shredding
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn254.jpg&quot; /&gt;Ptor in his element.  Always fun to ski around so much blue ice, especially in sweet powder! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Silverhorn256.jpg&quot; /&gt;Colin getting a bit of a face shot.  Not bad, considering there had been virtually no new snow in a couple of weeks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Rockies2013lores-26%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW catching up, after finally puttng the camera away.  Great turns all the way to the parking.  A super fun day.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident215.jpg&quot; /&gt;Ptor crossing the barely frozen Constellation Lakes.  Unfortunately the day didn&#039;t produce anything worth writing about as far as ski lines go, but it was cool to check out a new valley.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident237.jpg&quot; /&gt;The columbia icefields seemed like the best option considering the short weather forecasts and Colin and Ptor were psyched for Mt. Andromeda&#039;s Skyladde, the sunlit ramp right of center.  It&#039;s one of the most classic steep lines in the Rockies, and was fun to revisit it, as it had been 14 or 15 years since I had first skied it.    
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident219.jpg&quot; /&gt;Another early start
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident221.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Climbing through the first ice step
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident224.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nearing the summit ridge and getting good views of the Columbia Icefields.   A sweet crotch grab / hang loose by a stoked Colin!  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident227.jpg&quot; /&gt;Fine positions on the summit ridge 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Rockies2013lores-109%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW on the summit scoping the warm-up corn run into the south bowl. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident230.jpg&quot; /&gt;Ptor on run #1, Andromeda&#039;s south bowl.  We then toured back to the summit and dropped into the Skyladder.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bident231.jpg&quot; /&gt; Ptor in the Skyladder
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Rockies2013lores-131%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
JW in the upper part of the Skyladder 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0236.JPG&quot; /&gt;JW exiting the skyladder, photo Colin Haley 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_7572.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A view of Mt. Temple from the 3.5 couloir, (photo taken several years ago).  Our next objective was it&#039;s SW face which is the shaded one, that drops left off the summit.  And with 50+ cms of new snow, it was a memorable run! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Temple8.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With good snow coverage, we were able to skin all the way to the summit!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Temple17.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Almost there.  The weather was just good enough, although a whiteout on the summit made getting finding the entrance to the line a little bit interesting 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple241.jpg&quot; /&gt;Oh Yeah!  Finally getting a burst of sunlight and the views confirming we were in the right spot
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple242.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ptor, in the upper part of a long run. down Temples SW face.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Rockies2013lores-204%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I was stoked to be skiing on my Empires for this run, especially as the snow got heavier near the bottom 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple243.jpg&quot; /&gt; Colin, cruising down Temple
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple245.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ptor sending the snow flying on Temple
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple%20244.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple%20243.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple%20243.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/temple%20243.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/taxonomy/term/4">Skiing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/candadian_rockies">Candadian Rockies</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ski_descents">First Ski Descent</category>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2013 03:54:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">105 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rockies Ice</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/02/19/rockies_ice</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This post is going to be a quick and dirty.  No preaching, no spraying, no shameless advertising!   I&#039;ve been so busy with work, training, and life lately that blogging time has been sparse to say the least.  So until the next one, I&#039;m mainly just going to post a few pics of me for a change, thanks to Paul and Magda.  I don&#039;t usually post very many photos of myself but here&#039;s a few from some of the amazing Rockies classics I&#039;ve been on lately.  i wish I had some skiing photos from some of the neck deep days at the Rogers Pass I&#039;ve had, but it&#039;s too hard to stop and take them when you&#039;re having that much fun.  The ski posts will come soon as the days get longer and more interesting adventures begin to unfold.…  For now, here&#039;s some climbing b-roll, Canadian Rockies style... 
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/cragging%2055.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot;/&gt;Me, on the fourth pitch of Cryophobia, M8 225 meters.  Easily one of the best mixed routes in range!  Photo: Magda Kosior
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
me on the second pitch of the French Reality. Yet another multi-pitch mega classic!  Photo:Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Me on the second pitch of Nightmare on Wolf Street.  Another one of my vavorites.  The Stanley Headwall is in great shape shape this year!  Photo: Paul Bride
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first mixed pitch of Nightmare on Wolf Street with Magda Kosior on belay duty.  Photo: Paul Bride   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/cragging%209.jpg&quot; /&gt;Skate skiing is one of my favorite forms of training, and who better to do it with than my 27 month old daughter Zoe.  Here she&#039;s immitating me without the skis during a break.  &amp;quot;Faster Daddy faster&amp;quot; is what i mostly hear when towing her!     
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0487%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And here&#039;s a photo of where I&#039;m going in a week, for a week!  One of my favorite zones.  Hopefully conditions will be as good as the last two times.   
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/ice_mixed_climbing_0">Ice / mixed climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <enclosure url="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/sites/default/files/cragging 55.jpg" length="346543" type="image/jpeg" />
 <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2013 03:41:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">99 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Patagonia</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2013/01/08/patagonia</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
Patagonia &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%20700.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Cerro Torre, Torre Egger and Cerro Stanharhardt, as seen from the approah on the Torre Glacier.  The Ragni route on Cerro Torre approximately follows the left skyline. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&#039;s been a great 4th trip to Patagonia, and once again I got lucky with the weather.  Since I arrived on the afternoon of December the 10th, to the 2nd of January, Colin and I managed to get in 5 big days of alpine climbing (a couple of updates in the last blog post), which by Patagonian standards is quite good.  It was only on &amp;quot;Venas Azules&amp;quot;, the hardest route we tried, that we got thwarted by a storm and were forced to descend a mere 80 meters from Torre Egger&#039;s summit.  Despite it being the only &#039;failure&amp;quot;, it was definitely the highlight of the trip for me, as for me, the journey is far more important than the often overrated summit.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The last two weather windows fell exactly on christmas and new years.  On Christmas morning, about ten parties of climbers climbed the infamous Ragni route on Cerro Torre&#039;s west face.  I&#039;ve never seen an alpine route so crowded and so many ropes intertwining like macramé, so high above tree-line.  But everybody was good with it, the mood was festive, and everybody made it to the cumbre of Patagonia&#039;s most aesthetic Torre.  The climbing although only moderate in difficulty thanks to a well blazed trail to follow, was incredibly fun!   Weaving around so many wild fluffy rime mushrooms on a path of perfect blue ice.  To top it off, a natural tunnel right through the summit shroom led to the top.  It was exquisite! &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Because it was looking like big window, Colin and I hauled a light-weight tent, and extra food / fuel, with intentions of rappelling the north side of the mountain to the Col of Conquest, where we&#039;d camp and attempt Venas Azules on the south face of Torre Egger the next day.  This all went smoothly, and the following morning we started up Venas with no expectations.  We didn&#039;t even get a glimpse of the third pitch until we were right below it, despite being so close to it on the rappel.  It was natural tube facing just west enough that it was impossible to see until right below it, and otherwise the cross-chasm view revealed only a giant overhanging white mushroom with no possible climbing features.   A couple of easier thin ice and mixed pitches wrapped around to it.  Then a few rock moves led up to some steep rime, which I climbed onto.  Eventually the steep rime would gain an overhanging tube of perfect blue ice, but with no protection available, I&#039;d needed to find another way.  After down-climbing, I was able to traverse left a few meters to a splitter fingercrack up the face that offered great drytooling and protection.  After 15-20 meters of pure crack, it became possible to traverse into the tube.  The stemming and chimneying inside the tube got steeper and steeper until I was forced to exit onto vertical+ ice, which eventually led to a sheltered belay before the next overhanging corner pitch.  My biceps were barely recovered by the time Colin arrived at the belay.  I started up the next pitch as soon as possible with the first 15-meters of 85-degee ice going quickly.   The pace slowed as the overhanging corner, above took a fair bit of work to clean snow and ice out of the crack and find adequate protection.  With crampons skating off the smooth walls, it didn&#039;t take long before I pumped out and had to resort to some A1.  Colin got a nice combo of mixed ground, and tube climbing on the fifth pitch, and I got 20-meters up another tube on the sixth.  When the blue turned to white, I hacked a my way through a fin of rime on left, getting ready to get fully pumped on a few bodylengths of 90 to 95-degress ahead.  But the wind was suddenly howling and a storm was upon us.  Both us and our gear were instantly growing rime ice!  It was time to bail.  I clipped my last screw and lowered back to the belay.  The ropes were blowing sideways as we tried to rappel below and they had to be kept in coils hanging from the harness.  After a few airy and scary rappels, we were back at the col.  We climbed a 50-meter to get to the rappel line of the American Torre Egger route, and began down by headlamp.  The spindrift began to pound us as the storm intensified, and I missed the exit ramp that led to the fixed rappel line down the East face of Cerro Torre.  Now we were committed to making our own anchors all the way down into no mans land.  One particular rappel was very memorable.  Even with 3 directional pieces of gear in the rock, it was 62 meter&#039;s of completely freehanging rappelling.  Finally I was able to snag the rock with an icetool, and make anchor with only 2-meters of rope left.  It would have been the prussik of a lifetime had it not worked out!  Eventually we made it down safely, minus all our nuts, pitons, cordelletes, a few biners / slings, and a climbing rope that got stuck on a pitch impossible to re-ascend.  On the Torre Glacier we brewed as the eastern sky slowly became light, and by 7 am, we were back in our tent at Niponinos.  The window had slammed shut a day early and had made our escape slightly more intense that we had hoped for!  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
After three days of rest in town, we were hiking back up.  Plan A was to give Venas Azules another go, but temperatures seemed a little high, and the window was looking on small side for it.  Plan B was go rock climbing on &amp;quot;Festerville&amp;quot;, a route up the north ridge of Cerro Stanhardt that came highly recommended by friends.   On the 1st of January, the alarm went off at 1:30 am, while many in Chalten were still ringing in the new year.    We were at the Stanhardt Col by sunrise, and climbing in rock shoes shortly after.  By the time the sun rolled around it was hot enough to climb in t-shirts!  The positions and the quality of Festerville were superb and it was so nice to have the pointy stuff inside the pack for a change.  A true choose your own adventure up a smorgasbord of splitters, Festerville delivered the goods.  Some 15 pitches later, we were climbing around mushrooms on the summit ridge, and soon standing on the top of the highest one, enjoying calm winds and evening sunlight shining across the icecap.  By the time we rappelled Exocet and hiked back to camp, it had been a 27-hour round trip, and was once again the light of day was upon us!  Sure enough by the time we awoke in the afternoon, it was starting to rain.  Once again, the window was closed.  Time to hike out and go home! &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Summary of the trip: &lt;br /&gt;
Dec 12th - Guillot Gully, M5 5.9,Aguja Guillaumet&lt;br /&gt;
Dec 18th- Tobbagan, M6, Cerro Stanhardt&lt;br /&gt;
Dec 25th Ragni Route, AI 5+, Cerro Torre&lt;br /&gt;
Dec 26th Venas Azulas attempt, AI 6+, on Torre Egger (high point was approx 80 meters from summit)                  &lt;br /&gt;
Jan 1st  Festerville, 5.11b AI 3, Cerro Torre
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some b roll: 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2010.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Paul, Tony and Chris on the Torre Glacier - a force to be reckonned with 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2029%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On the West side of the Torre&#039;s at around midnight, while approaching the Ragni route under a full moon..  The Ragni route is the right skyline of Cerro Torre (rimed up peak on the left), and Venas Azules is the right skyline of Torre Egger - the rimed up peak in the center  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2038.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The top of Torre Egger at Sunrise 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2042.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you look really closely, there are about ten climbers in this photo, xmas day on Cerro Torre 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2044.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin, Sean, and Stephanne enjoy the first rays of the day on Cerro Torre 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2050.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bottleneck on the headwall looking up 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2051.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bottleneck on the Headwall looking down.  It just didn&#039;t seem to matter.   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2060.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Amazing views to the north from high on the Ragni route.  The southern Patagonia Icecap on the left and a sea of clouds hids the valley bottoms on the right. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2064.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sig-Bjorn leads the last pitch of steep ice and tunneling 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2066.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Belay at the last pitch 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%2088.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin and I at the summit 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20101.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Argentino climbers about three pitches below the top.  We passed them on our way down. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20132.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our tent site at the Col of Conquest wasn&#039;t quuite big enough for the entire footprint of our Firstlight. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20138.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The North Face of Cerro Torre looms above.  It was about ten long rappels from the mushrooms at the top to here. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20167%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin in the finger crack of the third pitch of Venas Azules 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20171.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin emerging from the overhanging tube on the third pitch 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%20187.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin starting up the fourth pitch of Venas Azules.  The north face of Cerro Torre on the right, and the south face of Torre Egger on the left  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Cerro%20Torre%202.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From left to right: Cerro Torre, Torre Egger, and Cerro Stanhardt.  Festerville follows the left skyline of Stanhardt 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%2023.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin on the first pitch of Festerville from the Stanhardt Col. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%2039.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A little higher up 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%2064%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
Colin on the steepest pitch of the route, a sweet 5.11b finger and hand corner &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%2089.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
Nothing but good times on Festerville &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%2099.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;form-item&quot; id=&quot;edit-files-upload-21-description-wrapper&quot;&gt;
Choose your own adventure country &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%20102.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Getting near the top of the rock climbing 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%20134.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin Leading the summit mushroom 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%20145.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The nice view of Cerro Torre, Torre Egger, and the Southern Patagonia Icecap from the summit 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Festerville%20152.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A summit fist pump! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/patagonia">Patagonia</category>
 <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 16:38:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">98 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Guy Lacelle </title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2012/12/22/guy_lacelle</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
As many have heard, I&#039;ve been presented with this years Guy Lacelle award.  Guy was a friend, climbing partner, and mentor to me.  Guy&#039;s psyche, modesty, and blissful approach had a strongly influenced me, and I found his achievements were incredibly inspiring.  I&#039;m deeply humbled and honoured that the award committee feels I share a similar attitude and values.  The news came as a surprise email, completely out of the blue, and I&#039;m overwhelmed it&#039;s been given to me.  Apparently, I&#039;m to receive some gear form his sponsors Petzl, Arcteryx, and La Sportiva.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Guy%20les%20mis.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Guy leading the second pitch of Les Miserables WI6&lt;/i&gt;+
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I certainly carried his spirit as I attempted various new mixed lines in the Canadian Rockies this fall, with varying successes.  There were some sweet sends, and as usual, some projects have been put on hold until next year, with high hopes of having more attemps to complete them.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/rimwall11.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;R. Slawinski avoiding unprotectable thin ice via mixed corner in the Canadian Rockies, during the anual fall time new routing binge &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I write, I&#039;m between missions amongst the imfamous Torres of Argentine Patagonia.  Guys spirit, amongst others are definitely present.  Colin Haley and I are partnered up and have climbed two alpine routes in the last week or so, and we&#039;re now packing for the next one.  The first adventure we had was up the Guillot gully on the east face of Aguja Guillaumet. It was generally an easy climb, with about 8 belayed pitches, but it felt pretty intense in high winds and cold conditions.  It&#039;s amazing how subtle changes in conditions or weather can make an easy route suddenly feel very real!  It was especially cool for me to reach a summit I had never been to, on a day that we were likely the only climbers to even bother leaving the valley that day, and within 48 hours of being here.  2300 meters of steep up and down, in 18 hours round trip from town had the legs screaming for days!  I suppose it was good training... Some more pics can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://colinhaley.blogspot.com.ar/2012/12/guillaumet-laps.html&quot;&gt;here on Colin&#039;s blog.  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Aguja%20Guillamet%2052.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Our second alpine climb was Toboggan, a 700-meter mixed route that ends at the Col de Suenos between Cerro Stanhardt and Punta Herron.  We had hoped to make the first integral ascent of this by taking it to either of the above mentioned summits, but the super rimed-up pitches above the col looked uninviting, out of condition, and at 8 pm, the night wasn&#039;t far off.  Had we had slightly better conditions, I think we might have gone for it through the night but prudently we opted otherwise.  As it turns out, we did what was likely the second ascent of the route and the first free ascent.  Most of the route being thin ice climbing up slabs, chimneys, and corners, with rock gear for protection.  Upon returning to town, we found out from Rolo, that we likely had considerably more ice than him and SIlvo on the first ascent in 1999.  All and all, it was a fun and worthwhile outing and took nearly 25 hours round-trip from our camp at Niponinos.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Torre%20approach.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Colin approaching the Torres! Cerro Torre on the left, Torre Egger
and Punta Herron in the middle, and Cerro Stanhardt on the 
right.Tobogan follows the gully / chimney system just right of the 
hanging glacier part way up Torre Egger. &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Tobogan%2033.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Colin coming up a slab of neve about halfway up the route.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Tobogan%2049.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Colin heading entering cruise control up another chimney laced with good ice  &lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Some sport climbing and bouldering has been keeping our blood flowing and fingers strong in the days spent in town between weather windows.   It seems like all the climbers in Chalten are getting a better than average Xmas window, so hopefully there&#039;ll be more cumbres to write home about soon! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Chimango.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Tony Richardson sending Chimango, a fun 7a amongst the Madsen Boulders, Chalten&lt;/i&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As good as it is here, I can hardly wait to start shredding the super deep pow at home in three weeks time!  
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2012 11:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">97 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Check Your Head</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2012/12/01/check_your_head</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/GetInline.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A photo of me taken by Joshua Lavigne on nearing the top of the second pitch. (Yes, we goofed around with camera gear, did some filming and photo work.  The beauty of climbing as a team of three!) 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Check Your Head  M6+R, WI 5+ 180m;  FA:Jason Kruk, Joshua Lavigne, Jon Walsh  November 25th, 2012 &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
This mixed adventure is well worth the long approach.  Skis are recommended.  You can see the upper half of the route from highway 93, and it lies at the right end of of the first main wall at the Storm Creek Headwall.  The rock is excellent and belays are mostly bolted, and at good stances.  For the most part, the drytooling is very positive in good cracks, and protects well with natural gear.   The best place to park is at the Stanley Headwall parking, approximately .8 km south of the Storm Creek Headwall fire break approach slope, which has a &amp;quot;no stopping avalanche zone&amp;quot; sign on the highway right below it.  The route itself lies in a big avalanche path, so stable snow conditions are needed to climb it.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Ski up the fire break, take the road to the left at the top of it to the creek.  Follow the creek up the drainage to headwall.  Ascend the fan to the base of the route, 2.5 - 3 hours.     &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Approach pitch: solo 30 meters of very thin WI2 (no pro), to an ice belay in a cave.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 1:  M6, 32 meters  - Start up a couple short ice flows and gain a left facing corner with good gear.  A couple delicate slab moves gain a short right facing corner.  Follow it for a couple body lengths to a left facing corner that leads to a snow ledge and a two bolt belay.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 2: M6+ R, 35 meters  - Take the groove straight up from the left edge of the ledge.  Move leftwards past  two pitons (only fixed pro on route).  The second is a very good lost arrow.  Once it&#039;s clipped, traverse left on small edges and continue trending up and left until another crack can be reached.   Follow it straight up and eventually becomes a shallow right facing corner,  that ends at a snow ledge, a two bolt belay, and the lower angle halfway &amp;quot;ledge&amp;quot;.  The second half of the traverse is a little bit run-out, but not the hardest part of the pitch.   &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 3: M5 25 meters  -  Head up from the belay, and then take a hard left where it&#039;s easiest.  A two bolt anchor is found just before the ice.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 4: WI 5+ 40 meters  -  The left side of the ice was thicker and offered the most protectable line.  Small rock gear was useful to protect the initial moves onto the thin curtain at the bottom.  We belayed at a protected stance from ice screws on the right hand side, before the final steep pillar.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Pitch 5: WI 4+ 25 meters  -  Straight forward high quality ice climbing to an ice anchor at the top.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Rappel notes:  It&#039;s a 57-meter rappel from the top of the ice to the highest bolted anchor.   Then a 45-50-meter rappel straight down to a 2-nut station at a hanging stance (drill battery died).   Then a 20 meter free hanging rappel to the ground.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rack: 2 60-meter ropes; 1 set of nuts, 1 set of micro cams, 2 sets of 
cams from .3 camelot to #3 camelot.  8-10 ice screws.  Pitons optional 
(we placed 2 and left them fixed).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0637%20Storm.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Two different angles of the climb, showing the belays and rappel stations 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0644%20Storm.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/ice_mixed_climbing_0">Ice / mixed climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/first_ascents">First Ascent</category>
 <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 14:52:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">96 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Recent favorites</title>
 <link>http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/2012/10/15/recent_favorites</link>
 <description>&lt;p&gt;
The last couple months have been one of the best high pressures I can remember in years.  On stat I heard was it&#039;s been the warmest summer in Calgary since 1881!  It was so nice in fact that it was impossibe for me to sit at a desk and share the photos, stories, or get much else done, as the mountains were calling....  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 I&#039;m lucky and grateful to live in such an amazing part of the world.  The Canadian Rockies are at my doorstep and the Bugaboos and Selkirks are a short drive away.   These three ranges never cease to blow my mind!  A few more reasons why I love being a canadian alpinist are (in no specific order):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
-I can always find talented and inspiring people to climb with on world class objectives
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
-There is so much variety in the mountain sports I&#039;m most interested in: sport, trad, ice and alpine climbing + unbelievable deep powder skiing on piste, off piste, ski mountaineering...  All in a relatively small area&lt;br /&gt;
-The development of the sport climbing scene in the Bow Valley is going off and provides the perfect training grounds to get strong, have fun, and prepare for harder objectives in mountains&lt;br /&gt;
-There is an abundance of multi-pitch adventure routes of all levels, in all disciplines of climbing &lt;br /&gt;
-The Rockies provide the world&#039;s most consistent, extensive, easily accessible ice and mixed scene - bar none!  &lt;br /&gt;
- First ascents -- Although the most obvious lines have mostly been done, some only once, there are still a lifetime&#039;s worth of first ascents to do, very much the opposite of Europe or the U.S.A..  I can share that because oddly enough, a little friendly international competition to get to them first would make them even more exciting!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
-Getting to the incredible stone and scenery of Baffin Island only requires a handful of airports, no passport, and one day of travel&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Here&#039;s a few pics from some of the climbing highlights from the last two months, starting with the Bugaboos:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%203.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh on the crux splitter of Hell or Highwater, Snowpatch Spire 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%206.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Chris and Simon working on yet another sick new project
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%2013.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh leading the first pitch of Chris&#039; other freshly completed new line: The East Columbia Indirect (mid 5.12), located just right of Hobo&#039;s Haven on the east end of the East face of Snowpatch.  Easily the highest quality route I&#039;ve done in a long time!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%2014.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Me leading the overhanging thin hands to fingers second pitch - photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualavigne.com/&quot;&gt;Joshua Lavigne  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%2017.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh leading the third pitch
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%2018.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Looking down at Simon and Chris climbing the route behind us.  Simon is seen here leading the second pitch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%202012%2020.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And looking down at Chris on the third pitch.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bugs%207%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&#039;s a line of the East Columbia Indirect as seen from the Crecent Glacier.  The fourth pitch finishes up the last pitch of the Power of Lard.  Although 4 pitches is a short route by Bugaboo standards, I&#039;m not sure of another route that has four pitches of this quality, sustained at 5.11+ with a few 5.12 cruxes.  Soooo good!  Start directly or scramble around via the the start of Sunshine Crack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/bugs%202012%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Applebee gang
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/bugs%202012%20(2).jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Lydia leading Sheldon&#039;s Corner, Easpost Spire
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Josh_eastpost.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Josh on a new route .12b on Eastpost Spire 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And then there&#039;s the Rockies.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0391%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Magda enjoying a really fun and new 12-pitch, 5.12- route on Ha Ling Peak above Canmore, called a Particular Manner of Expression.  Cudos to Jeph Relph and a variety of partners for putting this one up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0425%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://colinhaley.blogspot.ca/&quot;&gt;Colin Haley&lt;/a&gt; on the Greenwood / Jones route on the North Face of Mt. Temple. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0430%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This classic really exceded my expectations and I&#039;d highly recomend it.  Better than the other routes I&#039;ve climbed on Temples nordwand. Colin pulling a small overhang near the top of the rock.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0436%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Colin on the walking the line to the summit
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0448%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A raven joined us on top.  Here he&#039;s sitting right at the very peak, just a little bit higher than we made it!  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Howse.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On thanksgiving weekend, October 6-8,&lt;a href=&quot;http://raphaelslawinski.blogspot.ca/&quot;&gt; Raphael Slawinski &lt;/a&gt;and I climbed this line on Howse Peak - a combo of the NE buttress and some mixed variations  It wasn&#039;t the line we set out to do but as the Stones said &amp;quot;you can&#039;t always get what you want, but if you try sometime you just might find, you get what you need&amp;quot;.  We got what we needed, a great adventure up an iconic peak! 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0468%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Raphael looking for the way about a third of the way up
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0486%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our first bivi about halfway up 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0505%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The first pitch of day two was more sideways than up, as we deked out of the mixed gully system and back onto the ridge.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0516%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Good rock climbing on the buttress
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0479%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Raph following a little traverse between gully systems 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0521%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Back into more mixed gully action, Chephren Lake below 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0524%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Raphael sorting out the rope cluster in the sun 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0528%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Fun couloir climbing in the M-16 gully
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0539%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Still a bit of a cornice left from the revious winter.  Fortunately it was easily passed 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0543%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Raph taking in the view from the summit!   
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/IMG_0548%20copy.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Our second bivi sight.  After descending 1000m of the summit of Howse on our second day, it got dark as we arrived here.  The following morning, we ascended 600m to the misty Epaulette / White Pyramid col above the tent, and then descended down to the river Icefield Parkway beyond.  About 5.5 hours from the bivi to the road.  All said and done, it was a very satisfying and rewarding adventure!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following weekend, I couldn&#039;t help myself but go back to sport climbing.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bataan.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alpine climbing means a lot ot me, but it&#039;s pretty hard to beat the overhanging streaky rock at our local crags such as Bataan seen here.  It&#039;s just so much fun I don&#039;t think I&#039;ll ever be full.  &lt;a href=&quot;http://jennifercaye.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Jen&lt;/a&gt; onsighting a .12a in the upper photo and Jonny cranking below on a chilly mid october day. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/sites/default/files/Bataan%20(1).jpg&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/alpine_climbing">Alpine climbing</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/bugaboos">Bugaboos</category>
 <category domain="http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net/locations/canadian_rockies">Canadian Rockies</category>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 04:55:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jon walsh</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95 at http://jon.dev10.webenabled.net</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
